<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Banish'd duke, or, The tragedy of Infortunatus acted at the Theatre Royal.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12256081</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12256081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 163:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Banish'd duke, or, The tragedy of Infortunatus acted at the Theatre Royal.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 52, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monmouth, James Scott, --  Duke of, 1649-1685 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Baniſh'd Duke:</hi> OR, THE TRAGEDY OF Infortunatus. Acted at the Theatre Royal.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vivitur ingenio, caetera mortis erunt.</l>
               <l>— Nil non mortale tenemus,</l>
               <l>Pectoris exceptis ingenii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bonis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn,</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane;</hi> and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <l>GReat lofty Spirits, clogg'd with Clouds of Air,</l>
            <l>Soar high in hopes, and drown in deep deſpair:</l>
            <l>Whilſt diſcontented they turn, by diſdain,</l>
            <l>Their <hi>Theatre</hi> of Joy to Sorrow's <hi>Scene.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For proof, we'll demonſtrations to you bring,</l>
            <l>Of what befel a more than <hi>Popiſh</hi> King.</l>
            <l>And ſhew you one, ambitious for a Crown,</l>
            <l>Aſpire in Air, and in a Cloud fall down.</l>
            <l>We'll ſhew you Paſſion, ſuch as ne're was ſeen,</l>
            <l>Caſt up and cancell'd in a <hi>Roman Queen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>We'll treat you with a Monſter, in diſguiſe,</l>
            <l>Vail'd with pretence; and yet not cheat your eyes.</l>
            <l>And if you reliſh not our dainty food,</l>
            <l>We'll fill you up a Glaſs of Rebels blood;</l>
            <l>Blood that was ſhed and ſacrific'd to eaſe</l>
            <l>The rage of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Queen <hi>Papiſſa</hi> pleaſe.</l>
            <l>And to ſhut up the Feaſt, at laſt, you ſhall</l>
            <l>Have for a diſh, a Chriſtian Cannibal.</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Ens Rationis</hi> real, that's more rare</l>
            <l>Than any <hi>Show</hi> that's been in <hi>Smithfield-Fair.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then, for Deſert, we'll bring you from the Skyes,</l>
            <l>A Child conceiv'd, and ſwaddled up in lyes.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:3"/>
            <l>Whoſe Father was, and is not, ſeen unknown;</l>
            <l>Who, like the Oſtridge, doth his brood diſown.</l>
            <l>His Mothers have ſuppoſed real, been:</l>
            <l>This yet unknown, that an Imperious Queen.</l>
            <l>And leſt we Tantalize your Expectation,</l>
            <l>With Crabs, that ſet on edge this fruitful Nation,</l>
            <l>We'll haſte the Diſhes in, and feed your ſenſes</l>
            <l>With <hi>Hocus</hi> pranks, and Catholick pretences.</l>
            <l>Then rouſe your appetites above the Sphere</l>
            <l>Of Meat and Drink, we'll blow you up with Air:</l>
            <l>Air that ſhall make you vomit up your Diſhes</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Tranſubſtantiate Deities</hi> and Fiſhes.</l>
            <l>But leſt your quaſy Stomachs ſhould caſt up</l>
            <l>Your Dainties, drinking of the <hi>Roman</hi> Cup,</l>
            <l>We'll fill you out a Dram of <hi>Orange</hi>-juice;</l>
            <l>Will Antidote a Surfeit, and make Spruce</l>
            <l>Your drowſie Spirits: Then preſent your eye</l>
            <l>With th' end of Pride and Prodigality:</l>
            <l>Whoſe vain Reſults have, ſince the world began,</l>
            <l>Prov'd falſe, uncertain, and a great Trepan.</l>
            <l>From hence then Prudence learn, and be content</l>
            <l>With what you have, Diſtractions to prevent:</l>
            <l>And we will Objects, never brought to light,</l>
            <l>Firſt let you ſee, and after bid, <hi>Good Night.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Names of the Actors.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Romanus,</hi> King of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Infortunatus,</hi> Nephew to King <hi>Romanus,</hi> Baniſh'd for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Right to the Crown.</item>
                  <item>Don <hi>Alberlo,</hi> General of King <hi>Romanus</hi>'s Army.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cancellarius,</hi> a Timiſt, Favourite, and Councellour of King <hi>Romanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Manlius Clericus,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to King <hi>Romanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oxonius,</hi> a Church-Weather cock, Mountebank of State, and King <hi>Romanus</hi>'s Friend.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petrus Impoſtor,</hi> a Jeſuit, and Father Confeſſor to Queen <hi>Papiſſa.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Calamus Tremebundas,</hi> a ſubtile Sycophant, King <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>'s great Favourite.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Don Ferdinando,</hi> a Baniſh'd Peer of <hi>Albion,</hi> and pretended Friend to <hi>Infortunatus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Belgicus,</hi> a Collonel, and Favourite of <hi>Infortunatus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ingenioſo,</hi> Secretary, and Counſellour to <hi>Infortunatus,</hi> Baniſh'd by King <hi>Romanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flavius,</hi> Chaplain to <hi>Infortunatus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rogerus,</hi> a Clown, Knighted by <hi>Infortunatus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richardus,</hi> a Country Clown, who refuſed to be Knighted by <hi>Infortunatus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Papiſſa,</hi> a rigid Catholick, and Queen to King <hi>Romanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poviaena,</hi> Queen <hi>Papiſſa</hi>'s great Favourite and Councellour.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Form ſa Catholica,</hi> a Proſelite Popiſh N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mph.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Penelope,</hi> a Country Maid, in Love with <hi>Roger</hi> the Clown.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petrona</hi> an obſcure Catholick.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Ghoſt of <hi>Antonaius Calaſtrophus,</hi> Mayor, Conſtables, Page, Meſſengers, Executioner, Midwife, Children.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Baniſh'd Duke:</hi> OR, THE TRAGEDY OF Infortunatus.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT. I.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE a Village in <hi>Belgium.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Infortunatus, Belgicus,</hi> and <hi>Ingenioſo.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunat.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat Fate doth me thus to Subjection bring?</l>
                     <l>The Splendid Iſſue of a Potent King:</l>
                     <l>I, by Exploits, in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Valour ſhew'd, and Fortune did advance:</l>
                     <l>And for this Crime, my Royal Father ſent</l>
                     <l>Me from his Face, to ſuffer Baniſhment.</l>
                     <l>Ingrateful Cruel <hi>Romans</hi> ſerved thus</l>
                     <l>Brave <hi>Beliſarius</hi> and <hi>Andronicus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet I (in ſpight of Mortals) am deſign'd</l>
                     <l>To live and dye a Monarch in my mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belgic.</speaker>
                     <l>Better, Brave Prince, to live thus in Exile,</l>
                     <l>Than be Confin'd within Great <hi>Albion</hi>'s Iſle:</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57501:5"/>
                     <l>It is too ſmall environ'd by the Main,</l>
                     <l>Your ſwelling Orb of Greatneſs to contain:</l>
                     <l>On Earth's Vaſt Continent then live content,</l>
                     <l>Tho for a while you ſuffer Baniſhment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Belgicus.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Flavius.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince, your Father's lately dead and gone,</l>
                     <l>And now your Unkle do's poſſeſs his Throne;</l>
                     <l>A Popiſh Prince, that's neither juſt nor wiſe;</l>
                     <l>Seduc'd by Fopperies, Hocus pranks, and lyes.</l>
                     <l>Doubt not the Truth of what I do Relate;</l>
                     <l>Blame not Misfortune but ſubmit to Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>What? Is it true? And is my Father dead?</l>
                     <l>And now <hi>Romanus</hi> Crowned in his ſtead?</l>
                     <l>Strange News! Methinks the People have more Sence,</l>
                     <l>Than to be govern'd by a <hi>Roman</hi> Prince.</l>
                     <l>Are they who (like their Prince) were always free,</l>
                     <l>So eaſily Reduc'd to Slavery?</l>
                     <l>Poor Souls! who from their Courage now have fell,</l>
                     <l>May hence for ever in Repentance ſwell,</l>
                     <l>To think they've loſt the fit time to Rebel.</l>
                     <l>Rebel! Is it Rebellion to Depoſe</l>
                     <l>A Prince, long ſince, Depoſed by the Laws?</l>
                     <l>True Proteſtants, there, only ought to Sway,</l>
                     <l>To whom all Subjects ſhould Allegiance pay:</l>
                     <l>'Tis only ſuch that ſhould poſſeſs that Throne;</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Roman</hi> Succeſſour ſhould ſit thereon:</l>
                     <l>O Nation by Submiſſion quite undone!</l>
                     <l>Do they not know, if Chriſtians once but do</l>
                     <l>Give Gifts to <hi>Turks,</hi> they're after forc'd thereto;</l>
                     <l>For once Obeying, makes Obedience due.</l>
                     <l>What's to be done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you live thus in Baniſhment, and be</l>
                     <l>Kick'd from three Kingdoms, by Conſpiracy?</l>
                     <l>Muſt you, who was <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Darling, now</l>
                     <l>Unto an Out-Law'd <hi>Romiſh</hi> Scepter bow?</l>
                     <l>It is below your Spirit, therefore chooſe,</l>
                     <l>Rather <hi>One</hi> Head than <hi>Three</hi> Crowns thus to loſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le haſte to <hi>Albion,</hi> tho' my power be ſmall,</l>
                     <l>I'le either ſtand up right, or quite down fall.</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57501:5"/>
                     <l>Diſplay my Courage, when I come aſhore;</l>
                     <l>I'll fright the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and daunt the <hi>Scarlet Whore:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll uſe no Eloquence, but plead, with Swords,</l>
                     <l>That Right with Magnanimity affords.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Don <hi>Ferdinando.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>What? Still in Meditation! 'tis in vain;</l>
                     <l>Better you loſe your Limbs, than crack your Brain.</l>
                     <l>Rouſe up your Soul, if you your Country love,</l>
                     <l>Or love your Self, quick into Action move.</l>
                     <l>Do you not hear <hi>Romanus</hi> doth poſſeſs</l>
                     <l>The Throne, whilſt you Exil'd live Kingdomleſs?</l>
                     <l>Do you not know your great Ambition,</l>
                     <l>Lately expreſt, was to enjoy your own?</l>
                     <l>I mean that poor, griev'd and diſtreſſed Nation,</l>
                     <l>That's now Impos'd upon by Uſurpation:</l>
                     <l>To which you are true or ſuppoſed Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <p>(Many have ſaid what never One durſt ſwear.)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>And (laying by your Intereſt) it would be</l>
                     <l>(Since you with eaſe may ſet the Nation free)</l>
                     <l>One of the greateſt Acts of Charity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray tell me what is't you would have me do?</l>
                     <l>I cannot walk, nor ſpeak, nor think, for you:</l>
                     <l>For whether my Exerciſe be bad or good,</l>
                     <l>The well-bred <hi>Ferdinando</hi> doth intrude.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Call but a Council, and with them Adviſe;</l>
                     <l>A Council that's both Godly, Grave, and Wiſe:</l>
                     <l>To them propoſe whatever you think fit;</l>
                     <l>And then let them Debate and Judge of it.</l>
                     <l>Delay no more, Delays are ever curſt;</l>
                     <l>And Long-Bill'd-Birds do always ſing the worſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infor.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll take Advice of thoſe who're Good and True,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> I put Truſt in you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me a Cuckold be, my Wife turn Whore,</l>
                     <l>Let me ne'er Proſper, as I've heretofore;</l>
                     <l>Let me turn Coward, and be bath'd in Sin,</l>
                     <l>Kiſs my own Siſters when my Wife lies in;</l>
                     <l>If I on any terms whatever do</l>
                     <l>Betray my Truſt, or e'er prove Falſe to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57501:6"/>
                  <head>The SCENE King <hi>Romanus</hi> his Palace.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Romanus <hi>and</hi> Petrus Impoſtor</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>All my deſigns I cunningly have wrought,</l>
                     <l>This ſtubborn Nation to ſubjection brought.</l>
                     <l>I taught my Foes, e're they were ſick, to dye;</l>
                     <l>Now I'll profeſs the Art of Monarchy.</l>
                     <l>I'll make <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Neck my Yoke to bear:</l>
                     <l>Who will not love me, I'll compel to fear.</l>
                     <l>I'll keep no word with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> till I</l>
                     <l>O'rethrow their <hi>Church</hi> and ſet up <hi>Popery.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all my trembling Subjects ſhall obey,</l>
                     <l>Without enquiring what I do or ſay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Holineſs of Rome</hi> ſtill influence</l>
                     <l>Your undertakings, and be your defence.</l>
                     <l>We'll ſacrifice our Gods, and ſhall not fail</l>
                     <l>To uſe all means to make the Church prevail,</l>
                     <l>Which I am ſure can never well be done,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs you do contrive to get a Son:</l>
                     <l>This will ſecure your Kingdoms and your Crown;</l>
                     <l>And be a means to pull Uſurpers down.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Come work this Miracle, I love the thing,</l>
                     <l>To be the Father of a Popiſh King.</l>
                     <l>If thou'lt do this, I'll certainly reſtore</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome</hi>'s Revenues, which we kept back before.</l>
                     <l>I'll make my beſt and greateſt Subjects go</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Rome,</hi> and kiſs his <hi>Holineſs's</hi> Toe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> if you the <hi>Roman Church</hi> reſtore,</l>
                     <l>And make her ſound, as ſhe was once before,</l>
                     <l>And all thoſe wicked <hi>Hereticks</hi> but burn,</l>
                     <l>Who to the <hi>Romiſh Faith</hi> refuſe to turn;</l>
                     <l>We'll ſend you Relicks, Pardons, Holy Beads,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paul</hi>'s Teeth a Buſhel, two of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Heads,</l>
                     <l>Your venial Sins, Tranſgreſſions great and ſmall,</l>
                     <l>Paſt, Preſent, and to come, We'll Pardon all.</l>
                     <l>And when you're dead, for Songs you ſhall not want,</l>
                     <l>We'll canonize you, for a <hi>Holy Saint.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57501:6"/>
                     <l>And all who turn to <hi>Popery</hi> ſhall hove Power</l>
                     <l>To Drink and Swear, to Murder, Steal, and Whore,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Devil</hi>'s in that Man that would ask for more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Papiſſa.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>What Plots of Wit, and Stratagems of War,</l>
                     <l>In Brains quite void of Sence, do you prepare?</l>
                     <l>I am Great <hi>Albion</hi>'s ſtately head, and can</l>
                     <l>Out-wit the Projects of an Ancient Man.</l>
                     <l>Without your Aid, I quickly will pull down</l>
                     <l>All <hi>Hereticks</hi> before my Royal Crown.</l>
                     <l>My Subjects I will to Subjection bring;</l>
                     <l>I'm their whole <hi>Queen,</hi> and will be half their King.</l>
                     <l>I'il wear the <hi>Royal Breeches,</hi> and I'll make</l>
                     <stage>Throweth by her Gown and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Pair of Scarlet Breeches.</stage>
                     <l>All <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to tremble and to quake.</l>
                     <l>And if <hi>Romanus</hi> you offended be,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſnatch the Sword and rule the Monarchy.</l>
                     <l>The Roman Church in <hi>Albion</hi> I'll advance,</l>
                     <l>I'll have but one Religion as in <hi>France:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll tame my ſtubborn Subjects till they know</l>
                     <l>The flaming fury of a Popiſh Foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, hold, <hi>Papiſſa;</hi> for I can't allow,</l>
                     <l>To bear the Sword and wear the Breeches too.</l>
                     <l>You would unking and pull me from my Throne;</l>
                     <l>But you had beſt make haſte and get you gone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>How gone! I hitherto my ground have ſtood,</l>
                     <l>I'm come of more than Royal, <hi>Holy Blood.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Unkle is the lofty <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That doth command all <hi>Kings</hi> in Chriſtendom.</l>
                     <l>Then by our <hi>Lady,</hi> and the <hi>Popes Great Toe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>She pulleth him by the Cravat and Perriwig.</stage>
                     <l>You put me in a rage by ſaying ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>How? Confidence, This cannot be endur'd:</l>
                     <l>Call in the Guards, and let her be ſecur'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Cancellarius.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Great <hi>Madam,</hi> I'm aſham'd to ſee ſuch actions,</l>
                     <l>Which preſage more, and greater Court-diſtractions.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>A King's but like another Man to me;</l>
                     <l>Should he live Fopp, I will an Empreſs be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57501:7"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Was ever King Infortunate like me?</l>
                     <l>Who Married one below my Pedegree,</l>
                     <l>That now inſults and hectors, as you ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Ex. Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The SCENE</hi> Infortunatus<hi>'s Chamber: Enter</hi> Infortunatus, Belgicus, Ferdinando, Flavius, <hi>and</hi> Ingenioſo.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infor.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Members of my Council are but few,</l>
                        <l>Yet hope they're Worthy, Valiant, Wiſe and True.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You know my Father's lately dead and gone,</l>
                        <l>And now <hi>Romanus</hi> doth poſſeſs his Throne,</l>
                        <l>He was the Man that did undo us all,</l>
                        <l>Who Baniſh'd me, and did contrive my Fall.</l>
                        <l>But I'm reſolv'd with all the ſpeed I can,</l>
                        <l>To go for <hi>Albion</hi> and liſt every Man</l>
                        <l>That will prove Faithful to my Cauſe and me;</l>
                        <l>And ſet oppreſſed wretched <hi>Albion</hi> free.</l>
                        <l>Yet I would know your mind; e're we go hence,</l>
                        <l>In a deſign of ſo great conſequence.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave <hi>Sir,</hi> a clearer caſe was never known,</l>
                     <l>Than for a Prince to plead to have his own:</l>
                     <l>We'll haſt to Sea, both Men and Arms prepare,</l>
                     <l>Your cauſe is juſt, if you be Lawful Heir.</l>
                     <l>You ſhall have all the aid I can afford,</l>
                     <l>I'll be the firſt Man that ſhall go on Board.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>There's no neceſſity, at ſuch a time,</l>
                     <l>To clear our cauſe of any forged Crime,</l>
                     <l>Or to excuſe our ſelves of Treaſon, ſince</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Romanus</hi> ever was a Popiſh Prince.</l>
                     <l>Tho' <hi>Timiſts</hi> ſhould be guilty, and refuſe</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſtance to our Forces, let them chooſe;</l>
                     <l>Yet no true Proteſtants can aid deny,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs Self-Intereſt give their Souls the lye.</l>
                     <l>Then rouſe, <hi>Brave Prince,</hi> aſſure your ſelf that we</l>
                     <l>In all deſigns victorious will be.</l>
                     <l>The great Temptations that we do endure,</l>
                     <l>May drive us to ſo deſperate a Cure;</l>
                     <l>We're Baniſh'd, Broke, of all our Friends depriv'd,</l>
                     <l>Of Wives and Children too: And now arriv'd</l>
                     <l>In a ſtrange Country, of another Tongue,</l>
                     <l>E're we'll live ſo, our Foes ſhall eat their dung:</l>
                     <stage>[in great Paſſion.</stage>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57501:7"/>
                     <l>We'll unthrone Kings, the Popiſh Prieſts o'rethrow,</l>
                     <l>And make the Pope himſelf ſubjection know.</l>
                     <l>We'll drown <hi>Candaula,</hi> in a Scarlet Flood,</l>
                     <l>I'll dy my Sword in <hi>Babylonian</hi> Blood.</l>
                     <l>I long until I land on <hi>Albion</hi>'s Shore,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe a Tempeſt of Blood, Wounds, and Gore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Doubt not your ſucceſs but put all your truſt</l>
                     <l>In Providence, and in a Cauſe ſo juſt.</l>
                     <l>I'll preach and pray the Heavens to influence</l>
                     <l>Your Expedition, and be your defence.</l>
                     <l>I will ſtir up all Proteſtants to fight</l>
                     <l>For you, who ſtrives to keep them in their right.</l>
                     <l>I'll raiſe my voice above the beat of Drum,</l>
                     <l>And whether Men will or not, I'll make them come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold Gentlemen, I am not of your mind,</l>
                     <l>You waſte your courage in a cloud of Wind.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Romanus</hi> now is <hi>Albion</hi>'s great defence;</l>
                     <l>Who covers all his projects with Pretence:</l>
                     <l>And Tongues of popiſh Princes are ſet out</l>
                     <l>With guilded words, but poyſon'd at the Root:</l>
                     <l>His Subjects will believe him for a while,</l>
                     <l>And all accoſt him with a grateful Smile;</l>
                     <l>But e're a year go round, they'll find that he</l>
                     <l>Will prove perfidious, falſe like Popery.</l>
                     <l>Then all Religious Subjects will combine</l>
                     <l>To bring you home, and forward your deſign.</l>
                     <l>Therefore forbear, diſtractions to prevent,</l>
                     <l>And live another Year in Baniſhment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis ſtrange to ſee Men of politick wit</l>
                     <l>Nibble at all, and yet at nothing hit;</l>
                     <l>'Tis not obſervable what any ſays,</l>
                     <l>As long's a Council drives contrary ways.</l>
                     <l>Call in ſome <hi>Conjurer,</hi> that I may know</l>
                     <l>If we ſhall <hi>Albion</hi>'s Monarch overthrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Conjurer, <hi>in a prodigious dreſs, and with a formidable aſpect, ſtaring</hi> Infortunatus <hi>in the Face.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conjur.</speaker>
                     <l>Great <hi>Prince,</hi> I am come here, at your command,</l>
                     <l>To anſwer you whatever you demand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Tell me (thou <hi>Son of Satan</hi>) if I ſhall,</l>
                     <l>By force of Arms, make <hi>Albion</hi>'s Monarch fall?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57501:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conjur.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leo</hi> aſcends, and looks unto the <hi>Moon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>After he had look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on an Almanack or Conjuring Book.</stage>
                     <l>He roars and threatens to pull <hi>Taurus</hi> down:</l>
                     <l>And ſo I know, by this, your <hi>Planet</hi>'s good:</l>
                     <l>You'l conquer <hi>Albion</hi> without ſhedding Blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>This Aſtronomick Fool Nonſenſe doth prate,</l>
                     <l>But cannot tell our Fortunes, nor our Fate.</l>
                     <l>Old <hi>Antoninus</hi> could diſcover more</l>
                     <l>Than all th' <hi>Enchanters</hi> of the <hi>Scarlet Whore.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Canſt thou not in the twinkling of an Eye</l>
                     <l>Bring here the Ghoſt of old <hi>Calaſtrophy?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conjur.</speaker>
                     <l>—I'll try.</l>
                     <stage>The Conjurer goes under a Hanging, and maketh an hideous noiſe through a Reed or ſpeaking Trumpet, in theſe or ſuch Words.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rabbi David Eliazer, cum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Nicoloſa Vinſamor, mnmus, abſumus, abchaos, abdemor Gorgon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Ghoſt <hi>in a White Shroud.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Advance pale Ghoſt, that's in a Surplice, come</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Styx,</hi> or <hi>Lethe,</hi> or <hi>Eliſium.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fill up a Glaſs of State-Politick Wine;</l>
                     <stage>[Taketh up a Drinking Glaſs.</stage>
                     <l>I'll drink my Service to this grim Divine.</l>
                     <l>Old Gentleman, that looks ſo pale and green,</l>
                     <l>Good Health to all our Friends where you have been.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <l>What wicked Madneſs doth poſſeſs your Brain?</l>
                     <l>To bring me from my reſidence again?</l>
                     <l>In Life you brought in danger my gray Head,</l>
                     <l>Now you moleſt me after I am dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, hold, Old Man; And why a Wheedler ſtill?</l>
                     <l>I'll make you ſerve me now againſt your Will:</l>
                     <l>I'm half a Monarch, and deſire to know,</l>
                     <l>If I ſhall King <hi>Romanus</hi> overthrow.</l>
                     <l>My Father's Dead, and he doth wear his Crown,</l>
                     <l>A Popiſh Prince, therefore would pull him down.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Are there no Men alive could let you know,</l>
                     <l>If your Deſigns would take effect or no?</l>
                     <l>Go, go, and proſper, whilſt your Head is hot,</l>
                     <l>Though all will prove but like the former Plot;</l>
                     <l>Yet in a few days ſpace you ſhall with me,</l>
                     <l>In ſilent Grave, a Reſidenter be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Old Friend, Why doſt thou thus poſſeſs our Ears,</l>
                     <l>With Ghoſtly Maggots, Jealouſies, and Fears?</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57501:8"/>
                     <l>As tho' we knew not what and how to do,</l>
                     <l>In great Exploits of War as well as you.</l>
                     <l>He is invited o'r with ſighs and ſmiles,</l>
                     <l>By all the People within <hi>Albion</hi>'s Iſles,</l>
                     <l>And is aſſur'd, as ſoon's he comes to Land,</l>
                     <l>To have both Gold and Money at command.</l>
                     <l>There have been ſeveral Meſſengers here ſent</l>
                     <l>For him, the Kingdom's ruine to prevent;</l>
                     <l>For Popiſh Kings ſerve but to ruine Nations;</l>
                     <l>They keep no Word for Mental Reſervations.</l>
                     <l>Let your Prediction then be ſmooth and good,</l>
                     <l>Without effuſion of a Sea of Blood,</l>
                     <l>That our great want of Armour now may be,</l>
                     <l>Supply'd by you, in Magnanimity;</l>
                     <l>And we may boldly fight in ſuch a <hi>Cauſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lives, Church and State, Religion, and our Laws.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave off to talk, for I will ſpeak no more</l>
                     <l>Of your Deſign, than I have done before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou Church-Hobgobling, Mountebank of State,</l>
                     <l>Time's Weather-cock, confounder of my Fate,</l>
                     <l>I thee adjure, by Earth and by the Sea,</l>
                     <l>And all the dark Intrigues 'twixt thee and me.</l>
                     <l>By that broad Beard, and by thy Triple Name,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Babel</hi>'s Whore, and thy immortal Fame,</l>
                     <l>To tell me if to <hi>Albion</hi> I ſhall go,</l>
                     <l>And whether it will prove my overthrow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, go in haſte, and Sail the ſwelling Main,</l>
                     <l>I'll tell you more when you return again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Hence, get thee gone, Impoſtor of the Age,</l>
                     <l>And act no more on this inferiour Stage;</l>
                     <l>But that I know thou art already Dead,</l>
                     <l>I would cut off thy old Politick Head.</l>
                     <stage>[Draws his Sword and ſtrikes, whilſt the Ghost evaniſheth.</stage>
                     <l>Sure I can worſt a <hi>Babylonian ELF,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>[<hi>The Pope of</hi> Rome.</stage>
                     <l>When I can frighten thus Grim <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Meſſenger from</hi> Albion.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſeng.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brave Prince,</hi> I'm come from <hi>Albion</hi> to declare,</l>
                     <l>That you're reputed there our Lawful Heir;</l>
                     <l>And tho your Unkle doth poſſeſs the Crown,</l>
                     <l>His Subjects do not love him; pull him down:</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57501:9"/>
                     <l>A <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick who never ſticks</l>
                     <l>To falſify his Word to Hereticks.</l>
                     <l>His Queen's an Empreſs, and in ſpite of Fate,</l>
                     <l>She'll ſteer the Helm of Kingdom, Church and State.</l>
                     <l>She wears the Royal Breeches, yet muſt do</l>
                     <l>What e're the <hi>Pope of Rome</hi> commands her to.</l>
                     <l>And tho her Crimes and Wickedneſs abound,</l>
                     <l>(To ſpot the Skies, and <hi>Albion</hi> confound)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Holineſs</hi> (as all her Prieſts do tell)</l>
                     <l>Can ſave her Soul, and ſing her out of Hell.</l>
                     <l>She doth proteſt and ſwear by all that's good,</l>
                     <l>Taking her Oath in Sacraments of Blood,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Albion</hi>'s Church ſhall ſuddenly fall down,</l>
                     <l>And kneel before the Pope's great <hi>Triple Crown.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Bleeding Nation thus relief defers,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> turn your Petitioners.</l>
                     <l>We'll rather chooſe before your feet to fall,</l>
                     <l>Than be a Foot ſtool to a Cannibal;</l>
                     <l>That Cannibal which in ſubjection brings,</l>
                     <l>All Powers on Earth, Depoſing mighty Kings.</l>
                     <l>Our caſe the object of your pity make,</l>
                     <l>Since we, and all we have, do lie at ſtake.</l>
                     <l>Come o'r then, come, let not your Heart be faint,</l>
                     <l>You neither ſhall for Men nor Money want.</l>
                     <l>Ne'r fear your Fate, nor what <hi>Rome</hi>'s rage can do,</l>
                     <l>We ſerve our ſelves in ſtanding cloſe to you;</l>
                     <l>You ſtill have been the object of our eye,</l>
                     <l>Our confidence whereon we do rely.</l>
                     <l>Now Peers and People ſolemnly do vow,</l>
                     <l>To riſe and fall, to live and dye with you;</l>
                     <l>Yea, <hi>Nodnol</hi>-City, can and will alone,</l>
                     <l>Secure your Right, and ſet you on the Throne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>My Fleet is Rigg'd, I'll quickly go to Sea,</l>
                     <l>This Sword of mine ſhall ſet three Nations free.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbear, brave Sir, for what wiſe Prince relies,</l>
                     <l>Without aſſurance, on uncertainties?</l>
                     <l>Great Words, blown up with promiſes of Air,</l>
                     <l>Delude the Mind, but vaniſh in Deſpair.</l>
                     <l>Should you but go to <hi>Albion,</hi> and then find</l>
                     <l>Your expectation blaſted by the Wind,</l>
                     <l>You would your ſelf undo, three Nations bring</l>
                     <l>In greater Slavery to a Popiſh King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57501:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>If you prate more, this Sword ſhall run you thorow,</l>
                     <l>But all prepare to go on Board to morrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Petrus Impoſtor</hi>'s Chamber.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Petrus Impoſtor, <hi>in a Ghoſtly Popiſh Dreſs, with</hi> Formoſa, <hi>a Proſelite Popiſh Maid.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <l>My Ghoſtly Father, I'm come to confeſs</l>
                     <l>My Youthful Sins, and Wanton Wickedneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>Come let us have near converſe with another,</l>
                     <stage>[He proffereth to take her under the Hanging:</stage>
                     <l>And then I'll pardon all your ſins together.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I keep my <hi>Lent,</hi> and juſtly can deny,</l>
                     <l>With Ghoſtly Fathers in a Bed to lye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let me —</l>
                     <l>So ſmall a matter will not turn you Whore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a Sin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>It is no ſin at all,</l>
                     <l>For Fornication is but Venial.</l>
                     <l>But know you not that I can Pardon Sin?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not the right way that you do begin</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>If you be ſo ſtrait-lac'd, and will not do,</l>
                     <l>I'll have ten pound for Pardoning of you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Than be a Whore, I'll twenty pay in Gold:</l>
                     <l>But how can Pardons thus be bought and ſold?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a Journy-man, and 'tis my Trade</l>
                     <l>To ſpend my Lungs to gain my Daily Bread;</l>
                     <l>But, if you love your ſelf, with ſpeed, confeſs</l>
                     <l>Your Mortal Sins, and all your Wickedneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[She muttereth and confeſſeth.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>O theſe are heinous ſins, and there is none</l>
                     <l>That can forgive them, but the <hi>Pope</hi> alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What can be done then, in ſo great a ſtrait,</l>
                     <l>Since to confeſs. my ſins is now too late?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Queen of Heaven</hi> doth hang upon this Pin,</l>
                     <stage>[<hi>Pointing at the Virgin</hi> Mary<hi>'s Picture.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>And with a wink can pardon all your Sin.</l>
                     <l>If ſhe a tear drop from her gracious eye,</l>
                     <l>You're happy then to all Eternity;</l>
                     <l>If not, you are undone, then go and Pray,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Ave-Maries</hi> to <hi>our Lady</hi> ſay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>She muttereth and maketh Mouths on the V.</hi> Maries <hi>Picture, whilſt he goeth behind the Hanging, and ſquirteth water through its Eye, which ſhe perceiveth, and in paſſion,</hi> ſayeth,</stage>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57501:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Formoſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Can this your <hi>Holy Church</hi> commit ſuch things,</l>
                     <l>That doth Depoſe and ſet up Mighty Kings?</l>
                     <l>Is this one of the Miracles of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That to the World gives Laws and paſſeth Doom?</l>
                     <l>If this be your Religion, I will chooſe,</l>
                     <l>Rather than be of it, my life to loſe.</l>
                     <l>Farewel, Fare-ill, Impoſtor, I'll be gone;</l>
                     <l>Of Proſelited <hi>Papiſts</hi> I'll be none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>He proffereth to detain her, but ſhe will not.</hi> Exit, <hi>he following.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Limia,</hi> a Town, in the Weſt of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus, <hi>with his Forces from Sea, in a Gorgeous Scarlet Garb, and a Feather in his Hat.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>NOW we are paſt the dangers of the Main,</l>
                     <l>And ſafe arriv'd to <hi>Albion</hi> again:</l>
                     <l>Now is the time of Honour and Renown,</l>
                     <l>Then have at all, my Head againſt a Crown.</l>
                     <l>And tho' my preſent Forces be but ſmall</l>
                     <l>My Valours great, and I ſhall Conquer all;</l>
                     <l>Go then provide Men, Ammunition, Arms,</l>
                     <l>Surprize this ſleeping <hi>Iſland</hi> with Alarms.</l>
                     <l>Let Trumpets ſound, Drums beat, and Cannons roar,</l>
                     <l>To tell the Kingdom that I'm come aſhore;</l>
                     <l>And ſet my Standard up, that I may know</l>
                     <l>Who'll come or ſtay; who's Friend, and who is Foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
                     <l>We have no Standards, they were loſt at Sea,</l>
                     <l>With all the Train of our Artillery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <p>That's bad indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <l>But we may quickly take</l>
                     <l>Some Lady's Petticoat, and Colours make.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure, from that Standard, we ſhall never fly,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> are before our eye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57501:10"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Richardus <hi>and</hi> Rogerus, <hi>in a Country Dreſs, leading</hi> Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope <hi>a Country Maid, wearing a Scarlet Petticoat, gazing on</hi> Infortunatus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>What people's thoſe who boldly do intrude,</l>
                     <l>Within the Limits of my Latitude?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
                     <l>We, and this Maid, are only come to ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your Grace,</hi> and wiſh you all proſperity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I thought that you in my deſigns did pry,</l>
                     <l>And might ſurprize me with ſome Treachery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penelop.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a Maid, and have reſpect for you,</l>
                     <l>And if a Man, would gladly ſerve you too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Fair Nymph, I have a ſuit, deny me not,</l>
                     <l>Lend me a while your Scarlet Petticoat;</l>
                     <l>And when the Wars are o'r, I'll do to you,</l>
                     <l>A greater favour, and requite you too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penelop.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll give you it, the Complement's but ſmall,</l>
                     <l>If you will have my Gown you likeways ſhall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Giveth her Scarlet Petticoat to</hi> Ferdinando.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>To think of Maids now is a deadly crime,</l>
                     <l>But may accoſt you at another time.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Mayor with a Mace carried before him, Guarded by the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and his Long Staff.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mayor.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Mighty <hi>Prince,</hi> we heard you was come o'r,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Belgium,</hi> and Landed on our Shore;</l>
                     <l>Therefore we're humbly come, that we may do</l>
                     <l>You humble ſervice, and attend you too.</l>
                     <l>Then let us know what is your Sacred Will,</l>
                     <l>I am the City's <hi>Mayor,</hi> he <hi>Conſtable.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Go ſoon proclaim me <hi>Albion</hi>'s <hi>King,</hi> that I</l>
                     <l>May it reſtore again to Liberty;</l>
                     <l>(For I'm reſolv'd to make all Papiſts quake,</l>
                     <l>And reſcue Church and State, which lye at ſtake)</l>
                     <l>And then invite my Subjects to come in,</l>
                     <l>To fight with me againſt the <hi>Man of Sin.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mayor.</speaker>
                     <l>We will proclaim you King, and Forces raiſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſing <hi>Encomiums</hi> to your worthy praiſe;</l>
                     <l>We'll hazard all we have to fight with you,</l>
                     <l>Our VVives and Children, Lives and Fortunes too:</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57501:11"/>
                     <l>And we'll extol your Valour, if you dye,</l>
                     <l>VVith <hi>Monuments</hi> of Magnanimity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Mayor and Conſtab.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Trumpet ſoundeth without,</hi> Infortunatus <hi>is proclaimed King, with ſeveral Huzza's and Plaudities.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm <hi>Albion</hi>'s King, and would, at firſt, embrace</l>
                     <l>My Loving Subjects by my <hi>Acts of Grace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'd rather they ſhould love me for my Good,</l>
                     <l>Than fear and tremble for my ſhedding Blood.</l>
                     <l>And fair <hi>Nymph,</hi> if you have a friend or two,</l>
                     <l>But bring them here, I'll Knight them both for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Pointeth at</hi> Penelope, <hi>and Exit.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penel.</speaker>
                     <l>You <hi>Dick</hi> and <hi>Roger,</hi> objects of my love,</l>
                     <l>Reſpect to you, my paſſion now doth move:</l>
                     <l>I'll beg the King to Knight you for my ſake,</l>
                     <l>And afterwards both Officers to make.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                     <l>I am as much a Knight as he is King,</l>
                     <l>Till he this Nation to Subjection bring:</l>
                     <l>But if he'll Knight, and give me an Eſtate,</l>
                     <l>I'll love and ſerve him then, at any rate;</l>
                     <l>But till he give me fifty pounds <hi>per annm,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll rather hold the Plough, and ſerve my <hi>Grannum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll have no Honour, for a Landleſs Knight,</l>
                     <l>Is like a Lanthorn that can give no light:</l>
                     <l>I'll rather drive my Cart, and be invited</l>
                     <l>To fare that's courſe and mean, than ſo be ſlighted</l>
                     <l>For Gentlemen, who have not, muſt not work</l>
                     <l>For Honour's ſake, but fight againſt the Turk.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pene.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roger</hi> if you'll not Knighted be, I vow</l>
                     <l>I'll neither love nor marry'd be to you;</l>
                     <l>But if you'll Knighted be, we'll quickly wed,</l>
                     <l>And both (in State) go to our Marriage-Bed:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt we're advanc'd above our Pedegree,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall be MADAM, you HIS HONOUR be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather than loſe my <hi>Love,</hi> I'll bid good night</l>
                     <l>To Cart and Plough, and turn a begging <hi>Knight.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Honour will afford you every thing,</l>
                     <l>And we'll live great in preſence of a King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57501:11"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>What is the Reaſon of ſo long a ſtay?</l>
                     <l>We do but trifle here our time away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> theſe are my Friends, whom here I bring,</l>
                     <l>To be advanc'd to Knighthood by their KING.</l>
                     <l>This is my <hi>Sweet-heart,</hi> and that is my <hi>Brother;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Altho we do not favour one another.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Pointeth at</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>&amp;</hi> Richard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Madam,</hi> I will do any thing for you,</l>
                     <l>I'll give them Honour and Preferment too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>ROGER <hi>kiſſeth the Kings hand, falleth on his Knee, and is Knighted by King</hi> INFORTUNATUS.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Riſe up <hi>Sir Roger,</hi> Henceforth ever be</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Knight of Honour,</hi> Loyal unto me.</l>
                     <l>And when I'm ſettl'd on my Royal Throne,</l>
                     <l>You of my Privy Council ſhall be one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll prove a Loyal Subject till I dye,</l>
                     <l>I'll fight with Courage for your Majeſty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>A country Clown, if Knighted, may advance</l>
                     <l>As far in Battle as the King of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take here this Hat, and Coat, laid o're with Gold,</l>
                     <l>And prove a warlike Champion, brisk and bold,</l>
                     <l>That I may be convinced that there can</l>
                     <l>Be Courage in a Clown and country-man:</l>
                     <l>As for your Friend, if he will draw but nigh,</l>
                     <l>With equal Honour, I'll him dignify.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll be no Knight, I'll rather Chimneys ſweep,</l>
                     <l>If I work hard, at night I'll ſoundly ſleep,</l>
                     <l>I'll rather be contented in my mind,</l>
                     <l>Than be a <hi>Knight,</hi> and go beyond my Kind;</l>
                     <l>For Knights, without a competent Eſtate,</l>
                     <l>Muſt learn to beg, and curſe their rigid Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Baſe Slave, doſt thou my Favours thus deny?</l>
                     <l>And all my Royal proffers vilify?</l>
                     <l>But that thou art ſo much a Fop and Clown,</l>
                     <l>This Sword of Honour ſhould diſpatch thee ſoon.</l>
                     <l>No prudent Prince can think, in any caſe,</l>
                     <l>To gain a Rebel by an <hi>Act of Grace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hence then <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> from my preſence fly,</l>
                     <l>Leſs than the ſhadow of <hi>Nonentity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Richardus.</stage>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57501:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> your Army waiteth till you come,</l>
                     <l>I hear the Trumpets ſound, and beat of Drum.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Trumpet ſoundeth, and Drums beat without.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll march with all our Military Force,</l>
                     <l>We'll muſter every man, both Foot and Horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The SCENE</hi> Alba Aula Regalis, <hi>King</hi> Romanus<hi>'s Palace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter King</hi> Romanus, <hi>with his Privy Counſellours</hi> Alberlo, Cancellarius, Petrus, Manlius, Calamus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>You are my Privy Counſellors, and I</l>
                     <l>Am your bright Sun of <hi>Sovereign Majeſty;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You are <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s Wiſe and Watch-men now,</l>
                     <l>And under me the Kingdom's ſafeguard too.</l>
                     <l>Now I intend, if I poſſeſs my Crown,</l>
                     <l>To pull all Proteſtants in <hi>Albion</hi> down;</l>
                     <l>Then give me Counſel, that is grave and wiſe,</l>
                     <l>To proſeucte ſo brave an enterprize.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>Command all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereticks to turn,</l>
                     <l>And ſuch as will not, I will cauſe to burn;</l>
                     <l>We cannot think their ruin to prevent,</l>
                     <l>Who never eat God in the Sacrament.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, baſe Impoſtor, thou doſt boldly lye,</l>
                     <l>No man can make a Bleſſed Deity:</l>
                     <l>For God's but One, from all Eternity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>How <hi>Q— W</hi>— doſt thou think that a Crime?</l>
                     <l>I have made Twenty thouſand in my time,</l>
                     <l>And, as ſome Creatures their own Brood do eat,</l>
                     <l>I have devour'd them up like other meat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>Blaſphemous wretch, depriv'd of all that's good,</l>
                     <l>That doſt pretend to eat ſuch Fleſh and Blood.</l>
                     <l>Confounder of the Kingdom, and that's worſe,</l>
                     <l>Of Chriſtendom the blemiſh, ſtain, and curſe;</l>
                     <l>Perſwade not thus thy Prince to any thing,</l>
                     <l>That will him quickly to ſubjection bring.</l>
                     <l>No King, nor Court e're peaceable will be,</l>
                     <l>That is frequented by ſuch Ghoſts as thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Did we come here to hector, ſcold or dance?</l>
                     <l>Or ſpeak of things of greater importance?</l>
                     <l>Be ſilent then, and be contented ſo;</l>
                     <l>Or elſe I'll make you both to priſon go.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57501:12"/>
                     <l>But <hi>Calame</hi> give Councel if you can,</l>
                     <l>Since you are known to be a Subtile man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>If you would have the <hi>Church of Albion</hi> fall,</l>
                     <l>Grant Liberty of Conſcience to all.</l>
                     <l>Then when Lord <hi>Biſhop, Jack,</hi> and others fight,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pope of Rome</hi> comes in to plead his Right,</l>
                     <l>And then the weakeſt ſide will, out of doubt,</l>
                     <l>Joyn with the party that can bear it out.</l>
                     <l>Thus all your Clergy-men like Fox and Geeſe,</l>
                     <l>Will rather driven be, than loſe their Fleece.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Church of Albion</hi> is but near a Kin</l>
                     <l>To Mother Church, which they call <hi>Man of Sin.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Therefore it will be found an eaſy thing,</l>
                     <l>The Daughter with the Mother yet to bring</l>
                     <l>In favour; that the Romiſh Clergy may</l>
                     <l>Stop from the World, all means to read and pray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>You are miſtaken, <hi>Sir,</hi> there are great odds,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt <hi>Englands Church,</hi> and Popiſh <hi>Wooden-Gods,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As in thoſe Controverſies which we know,</l>
                     <l>You are run down, and daily find it ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſpeak it all, for Prieſts can ſwear and vow,</l>
                     <l>And Hector out, how much they'll act and do;</l>
                     <l>But if they will accompliſh their deſire,</l>
                     <l>It muſt not be by Learning, but by Fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>You're but the Spawn of Papiſts, and the Brood</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that now would ſuck your Blood;</l>
                     <l>They ſent you out, at firſt, to make a Rent</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Albion,</hi> without <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus your Religion is a Popiſh Lye,</l>
                     <l>Grown up and ſwaddled in State-policy,</l>
                     <l>Hood-wink'd, a Pilgrim of Apoſtacy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou wicked Monſter of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Compar'ſt with me that's Lucify'd within?</l>
                     <l>Religion muſt to Loyalty ſubmit,</l>
                     <l>And Conſcience give preheminence to Wit:</l>
                     <l>I would diſcover elſe thy Popiſh Maſs,</l>
                     <l>And then make bare the Romiſh Nakedneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Meſſenger <hi>in haste.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Frighted with warlike noiſe and beat of Drum,</l>
                     <l>I from the Weſt of <hi>Albion</hi> am come,</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57501:13"/>
                     <l>To tell your Majeſty an horrid plot,</l>
                     <l>Deep, dangerous, and ſuper-treaſon, hot.</l>
                     <l>Which Duke <hi>Infortunatus,</hi> in a Cell,</l>
                     <l>In ſhady Groves, and Dungeons dark as Hell,</l>
                     <l>Hath long contriv'd, and's likely to undo</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Intereſt, and your <hi>Greatneſs</hi> too.</l>
                     <l>He's come from <hi>Belgium,</hi> landed on our ſhore,</l>
                     <l>With all the Grandeur that he had before.</l>
                     <l>The Forces were but few which he did bring,</l>
                     <l>Now he's grown Great, and is proclaimed King:</l>
                     <l>He values not your Guards (he ſays) a pin;</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Volunteers, in Companies, come in.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>And are you ſure he's landed on our Shore?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſaw himſelf, ane heard his Cannons roar:</l>
                     <l>The Drums did beat, the Trumpets made a ſound,</l>
                     <l>As if they would the Univerſe confound.</l>
                     <l>He in a printed paper doth declare,</l>
                     <l>Altho' a Baſtard, that he's <hi>Albion</hi>'s Heir:</l>
                     <l>And ſpeaketh more diſgracefully of you,</l>
                     <l>Concerning <hi>Subdus</hi> and <hi>Fraternus</hi> too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I kick'd the Baſtard once quite out of doors,</l>
                     <l>Made him as low as other Sons of VVhores:</l>
                     <l>Now he's return'd to pull his Unkle down,</l>
                     <l>To wreſtle with me once more for the Crown.</l>
                     <l>I value not the Venom of his Gall,</l>
                     <l>But hope in time to make the Traitour fall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>How can he term himſelf the lawful Heir,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Albion?</hi> whilſt his Father did declare,</l>
                     <l>Before his Death, that he had never been</l>
                     <l>Wedded to any but his preſent Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> then grant me Liberty to go</l>
                     <l>T'oppoſe his Force, and prove his mortal Foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>When <hi>Albion</hi> once before was in diſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>Your Father did reſtore its Happineſs:</l>
                     <l>Now I'll intruſt his Son to ſave that Crown</l>
                     <l>From him who ſtrives t'Eclipſe and pull it down.</l>
                     <l>Take all my Foot-guard-Forces, great and ſmall,</l>
                     <l>Along with you, and be their General.</l>
                     <l>Confine the ſwelling multitude, till I,</l>
                     <l>In Horſe and Foot, afford you more ſupply:</l>
                     <l>I'll ſend you <hi>Gallus, Thorpius,</hi> and <hi>Stirk,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And theſe three Champions will do the work;</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57501:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>VVith them I'll ſend ten thouſand Men in arms,</l>
                     <l>To fright the Rebels with their freſh Alarms.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> I'll prove Magnanimous and true,</l>
                     <l>And Loyal; as my Father was to you:</l>
                     <l>If kill'd, I'll bid your Majeſty adieu.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Alberlo.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Papiſſa, <hi>in Paſſion.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Infortunatus</hi> now return'd again?</l>
                     <l>I take both Name and Perſon in diſdain:</l>
                     <l>Shall he a Baſtard born, an empty Clown,</l>
                     <l>Be Heir to <hi>France</hi> and wear <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Crown?</l>
                     <l>Baſe born, ill bred, and baſe till in his Tomb;</l>
                     <l>Baſe as his Mothers</l>
                     <l>How can he for a Lawful Right now plead?</l>
                     <l>Caſt, Out-Law'd, and condemn'd to loſe his Head.</l>
                     <l>I can out of this Pillow which you ſee</l>
                     <l>Produce a Royal Prince as good as he</l>
                     <l>Which may as ſoon, by Tranſubſtantation,</l>
                     <l>Be made his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> in this fruitful Nation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>She pulleth a Pillow from under her Gown &amp; throweth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather than he ſhall wear <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Crown,</l>
                     <l>I'll burn my Surplice, and throw by my Gown,</l>
                     <l>Renounce the Clergy, cut the Church aſunder,</l>
                     <l>And turn <hi>Bonarges,</hi> or a Son of Thunder:</l>
                     <l>Tho old, I'll be a Goſpel-Granadeer,</l>
                     <l>And roar in ſmoak, like <hi>Babels</hi> Cannoneer.</l>
                     <l>I, with the carnal Sword, my Flock ſhall feed;</l>
                     <l>And preach ſuch Doctrine, as ſhall make them bleed:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt every word, Granado-like, ſhall ſmell</l>
                     <l>Of Fire and Brimſtone, that came up from Hell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Don Ferdinando,</hi> that's cunning in deceit,</l>
                     <l>Declar'd a Rebel both to Church and State,</l>
                     <l>Is with th' Uſurper, and commands his Horſe;</l>
                     <l>And bears the rule of all his warlike Force:</l>
                     <l>Send him a Pardon of his former crimes,</l>
                     <l>Committed now, and at all other times,</l>
                     <l>He will betray the Traitor, with theſe few</l>
                     <l>Deluded <hi>Myrmidons,</hi> that trouble you:</l>
                     <l>Thus you will ſave much blood from being ſpilt,</l>
                     <l>Until you hang the Rebels for their Guilt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I do approve your Council, and I'll go</l>
                     <l>With ſpeed, and ſerve the Grand Uſurper ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57501:14"/>
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Infortunatus</hi>'s Quarters.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus, Ferdinando, Flavius, <hi>and</hi> Ingenioſo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I've call'd you here in haſte, to know if I</l>
                     <l>Shall ſtill go on, or my deſign lay by.</l>
                     <l>You ſee thoſe Peers and Nobles that did vow</l>
                     <l>To aid me with their Lives and Money too,</l>
                     <l>Have prov'd perfidious, been but Traps and Snares,</l>
                     <l>To draw me in a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of Cares.</l>
                     <l>If I fly back again to whence I came,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> rage will flouriſh to a flame;</l>
                     <l>If I reſolve the Romaniſts to fight,</l>
                     <l>And ſhould be beat, and put unto the flight,</l>
                     <l>Then all thoſe poor men now that follow me,</l>
                     <l>To Queen <hi>Papiſſa</hi> ſacrific'd will be.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alberlo</hi> rampant to reſiſt me's come,</l>
                     <l>With men well diſciplin'd by beat Drum:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt all my Forces (plainly to confeſs)</l>
                     <l>Are raw, unarm'd, and I am moneyleſs.</l>
                     <l>From ſorrow's Scene I do contemplate now</l>
                     <l>What baſe deceituful people's brought me to.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you (who was the Champion of the Nation,</l>
                     <l>The Kingdom's Boaſt, and <hi>Europe</hi>'s Admiration,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe warlike Sword made <hi>Germany</hi> to bleed,</l>
                     <l>And all King <hi>David</hi>'s worthies did exceed)</l>
                     <l>So ſoon caſt down? and thus compell'd to be</l>
                     <l>Void of your wonted Magnanimity?</l>
                     <l>This Sword of mine, with irreſiſtleſs blows,</l>
                     <l>Shall gain the day, and diſſipate our Foes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferg.</speaker>
                     <l>A man's but one, and every Musket Ball,</l>
                     <l>If ſhot with care, can make a Captain fall.</l>
                     <l>But there's no fear but we ſhall gain the Day,</l>
                     <l>If you'll prove true, and do half what you ſay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>You with <hi>Alberlo</hi> once was ſworn Brother,</l>
                     <l>To aid, to live and die with one another;</l>
                     <l>Now is the time to try if he'll be true,</l>
                     <l>By bringing all his Forces o're to you.</l>
                     <l>Send him a Letter then, and I ſhall find</l>
                     <l>A way to ſend it, and to pump his mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57501:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>What you do ſay I greatly do approve</l>
                     <l>I'll mind <hi>Alberlo</hi> of his former love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll write a more than preſſing Letter too,</l>
                     <l>To ſee what Wit and Loyalty can do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>With ſpeed and care then write as I command,</l>
                     <l>And I to what you write will put my hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Ferdinando.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Belgicus</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
                     <l>I came to tell <hi>your Majeſty</hi> that I</l>
                     <l>Have fought a Party of the Enemy.</l>
                     <l>We went to forrage in a little Town,</l>
                     <l>And from our Horſes as we lighted down,</l>
                     <l>Some Rebels rampant came in great diſdain,</l>
                     <l>But run the Gantlet backward through the Lane.</l>
                     <l>We were but ſixty, and they eighty ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>The bruſh was hot, but ſcarce an half hour long:</l>
                     <l>We killed Six, and they to us one man,</l>
                     <l>Then valiantly with whip and ſpur they ran.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>The News is good, may it be ever ſo</l>
                     <l>Until I work <hi>Romanus</hi> overthrow:</l>
                     <l>But ſoon return unto the Camp, and I</l>
                     <l>Will keep in mind your Magnanimity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Belgicus.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Ferdinando.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I've written a Letter of tranſcendent ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>As rich in Loyalty as Eloquence:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> be pleas'd, but once to read it o're,</l>
                     <l>And then, as you think fit, make leſs or more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Infortunatus <hi>readeth the Letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Entirely Beloved Couſin,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Experience of your former Reſpects prompteth me, at preſent, to write to you with the greater aſſurance of your Loving Acceptance, and put you in Remembrance of our former favours, upon the account of which, I earneſtly requeſt you (for the reſpect you owe to Church and State, and the particular Intereſt of every honeſt man) to aſſiſt me with your beſt advice, how to behave my ſelf in ſo great an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and to come over and joyn your Forces with ours; that we may ſettle every thing on a right Baſe, and the Kingdom may be freed from the vengeance of Popery, which hangeth over the Head of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57501:15"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57501:15"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57501:16"/>theſe three Languiſhing Nations. Which if you will be pleaſed to do, you will not only make your ſelf Famous to all ſucceeding Ages, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuing this Nation from the flaming rage of Popery, but alſo promote yourſelf above the power and revenge of your greateſt Enemies, and infinitely oblige me to be</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your Everlaſting Friend, &amp;c.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>With ſpeed and privacy, as I command,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Ingenioſo.</stage>
                     <l>Convey this Letter to <hi>Alberlo</hi>'s hand:</l>
                     <l>If he will grant me what I now require,</l>
                     <l>I'll grant in Greatneſs what he can deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Send likewiſe this, wherein with deepeſt ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>I do accoſt his <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Excellence:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perſwading him to joyn both Foot and Horſe,</l>
                     <l>To our Religious Military Force:</l>
                     <l>If he my earneſt ſuit ſlight or deny,</l>
                     <l>This Sword of mine ſhall make <hi>Alberlo</hi> dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Ferdin.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll ſend them both in haſte, and none ſhall know</l>
                     <l>From whence they come, or whether they do go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm jealous of what <hi>Ferdinando</hi> ſaid;</l>
                     <l>Pray let his Letter be in publick read.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Then quickly read it o're, that I may know</l>
                     <l>If he will prove a counterfeit or no.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Flavius <hi>breaketh open, and readeth the Letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellence,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I thought it convenient to accoſt, and humbly acquaint you with the condition of King <hi>Infortunatus</hi>'s Army; the number whereof is but few, and thoſe badly diſciplin'd and arm'd, ſo that it will be no hard matter to overthrow him and his weak Forces: But if you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade King <hi>Romanus</hi> (to whom I owe my Allegiance) to pardon me all my former Crimes, Treaſons and Conſpiracies whereof I am guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, againſt him and his late Brother, and for which I am caſt, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law'd, and condemn'd; I will ſoon cruſh the power of our new King, and ſave the Nation the trouble and expence of a bloody War. Therefore (with all ſpeed and privacy) communicate your mind to</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your Excellency's Faithful Friend, and Humble Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Is <hi>Ferdinando</hi> (whom, for Truth and Zeal</l>
                     <l>And mighty words, no Age could parellel)</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57501:16"/>
                     <l>Become a Rogue? and turn'd my mortal Foe?</l>
                     <l>Who's been my Sharer both in Weal and Woe.</l>
                     <l>Go bring him back; for this perfidious Plot,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Pointeth at</hi> Ingen.</stage>
                     <l>I'll ſee the Raſcal in my preſence ſhot.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Ingenioſo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>In whom can Kings put confidence? ſince he,</l>
                     <l>Pretending to ſo much Fidelity,</l>
                     <l>Brought to the Teſt, is found a timerous Slave,</l>
                     <l>A Timiſt, Traytor, and a Turn-Coat Knave?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>His Death ſhall to ſucceeding Ages be</l>
                     <l>Eſteem'd a Monument of Treachery.</l>
                     <l>That all who curſe, with a vindictive hate,</l>
                     <l>May wiſh their Foes to meet with ſuch a Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Ingenioſo</hi> with <hi>Ferdinando</hi> guarded with Souldiers, and his hands tyed behind him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Monſter of men, thou <hi>Judas</hi> in diſguiſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou Devil vail'd with Perjuries and Lyes;</l>
                     <l>Perfidious wretch, how durſt thou once deſign</l>
                     <l>Me to betray, and ruin all that's mine?</l>
                     <l>I never thought thee ill, but ever good,</l>
                     <l>And in thy quarrel oft-times ſpent my Blood;</l>
                     <l>And doſt thou thus require me, who for thee,</l>
                     <l>Have run ſuch hazards, both by Land and Sea?</l>
                     <l>Come tye him to the Stake, and let him know</l>
                     <l>The fury of a Friend turn'd to a Foe:</l>
                     <l>I'll ſee him ſhot to death, that Traytors all</l>
                     <l>May take example from his Tragick fall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Two Souldiers tye him, and make ready their Muſkets to ſhoot him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Mercy, O mercy, I for mercy cry,</l>
                     <l>You need no ſhots here, I for fear ſhall dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbear awhile, your Muskets both lay by,</l>
                     <l>Until we hear the Traytors Legacy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Souldiers lay by their Muskets.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>Some pity on me for your Goodneſs take,</l>
                     <l>Forgive me for my Wife and Childrens ſake:</l>
                     <l>I ſwear by all that's good, I'll prove to you,</l>
                     <l>Henceforth, a Subject faithful, good and true.</l>
                     <l>This is the firſt beginning of your Reign;</l>
                     <l>Stain not your hands with this poor blood of mine:</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57501:17"/>
                     <l>I have been ſtill partaker of your loſſes,</l>
                     <l>And born the burden of your Royal croſſes:</l>
                     <l>Now let your Candour and your Innocence</l>
                     <l>Blot out my crime, and cover my offence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I know you have been ſharer in my Fate,</l>
                     <l>Alſo the object of my Unkle's hate:</l>
                     <l>But how could you like <hi>Judas</hi> go aſtray,</l>
                     <l>And proffer me ſo-baſely to betray?</l>
                     <l>To Popiſh hands that ne're did <hi>Albion</hi> good,</l>
                     <l>But lov'd to ſhed and ſuck the Subjects Blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>This is the firſt time that I went aſtray,</l>
                     <l>Yet never did intend you to betray:</l>
                     <l>I with <hi>Alberlo</hi> ſeemingly combin'd,</l>
                     <l>Only to know the ſecrets of his mind;</l>
                     <l>Which ſuddenly I would have brought to you,</l>
                     <l>To be reſolv'd the better what do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <p>That's more indeed, than hitherto I knew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <p>You may believe what I affirm is true:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Then looſe my <hi>Ferdinando;</hi> let him be</l>
                     <l>A faithful Friend and Councellour to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Where is the Sword of Juſtice? ſuch a King</l>
                     <l>Is like a Honey-Bee without a Sting.</l>
                     <l>I'd ſeldome ſave a Law-Condemned Man,</l>
                     <l>For ſure the Rogue will hang me if he can.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Belgicus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alberlo</hi>'s Men are quartered here hard by;</l>
                     <l>By Two's and Threes, in Villages they lye.</l>
                     <l>Come, let us go, in ſilence of the Night,</l>
                     <l>We'll either kill, or put them all to Flight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Your News is good, and your Advice is better,</l>
                     <l>Than all the Wit in <hi>Ferdinando</hi>'s Letter.</l>
                     <l>I ne'r was bred a Coward, nor can kill</l>
                     <l>Poor Men aſleep, that never did me ill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
                     <l>There is another thing that we may do;</l>
                     <l>(For Souldiers ſhould be Wiſe and Valiant too)</l>
                     <l>We may ſurprize them in their Beds aſleep,</l>
                     <l>And afterwards them in cloſe Priſon keep,</l>
                     <l>As Hoſtages; which may, in time, augment</l>
                     <l>Our Number; and our Enemies prevent</l>
                     <l>From being cruel, 'gainſt our men, which they</l>
                     <l>May Captives take, and in their fury ſlay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57501:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>In policy it were a deadly a crime,</l>
                     <l>To ſlip th' occaſion of ſo fit a time,</l>
                     <l>Wherein we may our Enemies o'recome,</l>
                     <l>Without the noiſe of Trumpet or of Drum.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Inge.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let us go, and with a Warlike Slight,</l>
                     <l>Confound our Foes, which rob us of our Right.</l>
                     <l>'Tis fitter we them ſleeping Captives take,</l>
                     <l>Than that they Hang us up when we're awake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I will not condeſcend to any thing,</l>
                     <l>That ſtains the Reputation of my King;</l>
                     <l>It is below <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to be</l>
                     <l>Tainted with ſuch Puſillanimity.</l>
                     <l>We'll fight them fairly in the open field;</l>
                     <l>For, on our ſide, I'm ſure no man will yield.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it be ſo, your counſel I advance;</l>
                     <l>I'll let them ſee ſome ſtratagems of <hi>France:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll ſhew them Conduct both and Courage too,</l>
                     <l>And what Great Spirits, if provok'd, can do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus, Belgicus, <hi>and</hi> Flavius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou wicked wretch, that doſt contrive our fall, <hi>To</hi> Ferd.</l>
                     <l>Thy cruel counſel will undo us all:</l>
                     <l>Thy heart doth always give thy tongue the lye;</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt void of Courage, Wit, and Honeſty.</l>
                     <l>Come, draw that bloody Sword, wherewith you boaſt</l>
                     <l>To Conquer all, and kill <hi>Alberlo</hi>'s Hoſt:</l>
                     <l>I'll try your Valour, tho' you ſeem to be</l>
                     <l>A Great <hi>Goliah</hi> in reſpect of me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll neither fight, nor yet contrive your fall,</l>
                     <l>But find a way how to outwit you all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>Pretending Coward, bane of Church and State,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thou wilt not fight, I'll break thy pate:</l>
                     <stage>Striketh him ſeveral blows over the head, till the blood runneth down.</stage>
                     <l>Thou weather-cock, thy baſe deceitful Head</l>
                     <l>Will make thy name ſtink, after thou art dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <l>Murder, O murder, hold your Sword, elſe I</l>
                     <l>Shall be uncivil, and for fear will dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus <hi>and</hi> Belgicus <hi>in haſte.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <p>What noiſe was this I heard?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ingen.</speaker>
                     <l>No noiſe at all,</l>
                     <l>My Friend did only act the General.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Meſſenger from</hi> Alberlo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſeng.</speaker>
                     <l>Here I am from <hi>Alberlo</hi> come to bring</l>
                     <l>A Letter to your late Proclaimed King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57501:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Come hither then, for I am he whom you</l>
                     <l>Receiv'd command to give the Letter too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He taketh and readeth the Letter.</stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>Since you are but an Ape of Majeſty, I know not by what Title to accoſt you, being neither King nor Subject: But in ſhort, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanling all our former ties of Friendſhip, I will not be induced to betray my Truſt, and undeſerve that Confidence which King <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> hath placed in me; neither is it proper for me (tho it were not too late) to give you any advice, but it had been better for you to have ſtaid where you was, than to have come over here to put the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both to expence and trouble, and work your own overthrow, with the ruin of thoſe poor Men who have joined with you in ſo deſperate an Adventure; who will be reputed and ſuffer as Traytors, for proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your Treaſonable Deſigns, which really is both the grief and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your once real Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>And doth <hi>Alberlo</hi> thus requite me now,</l>
                     <l>For all my ſervice done and favours too?</l>
                     <l>I was his Friend ſtill in my Father's time,</l>
                     <l>To fight now for three Kingdoms is a crime.</l>
                     <l>I'll make him feel my Rage, and likewiſe know,</l>
                     <l>That hence I'll prove his everlaſting Foe.</l>
                     <l>I'll give him Battle ſoon, in open field,</l>
                     <l>And make him feel the Sword that ne'r did yield.</l>
                     <l>Go tell your Maſter, in <hi>Segeia</hi> plain,</l>
                     <stage>To the Meſſenger</stage>
                     <l>I'll give him Battel, tho I ſhould be ſlain:</l>
                     <l>To morrow morning, e're it be high noon,</l>
                     <l>I'll gain or loſe great <hi>Albions</hi> Royal Crown.</l>
                     <l>Go <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> muſter all our Force,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall command the Foot, and you the Horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm ſet on edge to hear <hi>Alberlo</hi> boaſt,</l>
                     <l>He talks as we were ruined and loſt:</l>
                     <l>His ſawcy Letter either tear or burn,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Execunt</hi> Infort. Belgicus, <hi>and</hi> Flavius.</stage>
                     <l>In clouds of ſmoak we'll ſend him a return.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſeng.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you <hi>Don Ferdinando?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <p>I am the Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſeng.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I have here to you,</l>
                     <l>A Letter, and a private Paper too,</l>
                     <l>I brought them from <hi>Alberlo</hi> in my Shooe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Taketh the Letter out of his Shooe.</stage>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57501:18"/>
                  <stage>Ferdinando <hi>taketh the Letter, and private Paper, and readeth them in haſte, and then ſpeaketh to the</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferdin.</speaker>
                     <l>Go quickly, tell your Maſter that I'm ſtill</l>
                     <l>His real Friend, and will obey his will.</l>
                     <l>Let him draw up his Forces one, and all,</l>
                     <l>And meet us, tho his army ſhould be ſmall.</l>
                     <l>I can find out a Thouſand pretty things,</l>
                     <l>That will undo and ruin Petty Kings.</l>
                     <l>I will do more, not by my Sword but Wit,</l>
                     <l>Than I to Ink and Paper will commit.</l>
                     <l>Only go tell <hi>Alberlo</hi> that I will,</l>
                     <l>Prove his true Friend, and humble Servant ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Meſſen.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Alberlo</hi>'s Quarters.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alberlo, <hi>and</hi> Manlius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm vext that King <hi>Infortunatus</hi> thought</l>
                     <l>That I for Gold, or Greatneſs would be bought.</l>
                     <l>I value not Promotion, whilſt I</l>
                     <l>Am Great enough, unſtain'd in Loyalty.</l>
                     <l>And tho Religion now doth lye at ſtake,</l>
                     <l>I'll take no notice, for <hi>Romanus</hi> ſake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>By <hi>George,</hi> and by this Py-bald coat of mine. </l>
                     <stage>His Surpleſs.</stage>
                     <l>I rather be a Duke, than a Divine.</l>
                     <l>You're great enough, indeed, but by my Miter,</l>
                     <l>I'll prove, in time of War, as good a fighter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>You're a couragious Rampant Church-man here,</l>
                     <l>And will on Service fight but in the Rear;</l>
                     <l>And ſcold at diſtance, as a Cannoneer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Meſſenger <hi>in haſte.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I've done your meſſage, and in haſte do bring,</l>
                     <l>You back another from the ſtart-up King,</l>
                     <l>To morrow morning, e're it be high Noon,</l>
                     <l>He'll give you Battle, gain or loſe his Crown.</l>
                     <l>His Forces are but few, all torn and rent,</l>
                     <l>Ill diſciplin'd, his Ammunition's ſpent.</l>
                     <l>But he ſpeaks Great, and will, unleſs he lye,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Romanus</hi> power, and all his force defy;</l>
                     <l>And make your Army like the Duſt to fly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57501:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <p>But what did old <hi>Don Ferdinando</hi> ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>He vows, that he his Maſter will betray.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                     <p>May he prove true to me, falſe to his King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>A Traytor is a neceſſary thing.</l>
                     <l>But once a Knave, Rogue, and a great Trapan,</l>
                     <l>Can ne're be truſted, like an honeſt man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                     <l>If he be Rogue enough, I will him bring,</l>
                     <l>Once more in Favour with <hi>Romanus</hi> King.</l>
                     <l>And if his, Treaſon take a good Effect,</l>
                     <l>I from the Hangman's hands ſhall ſave his neck.</l>
                     <l>But wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to morrow, e're it be quite light,</l>
                     <l>Have all my men in readineſs to fight.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Segeia</hi> Plain.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus, <hi>with Officers and Souldiers, and draw up in one ſide of the</hi> Scene, <hi>in Battle array, Armed and ready to fight, Drums beating, Trumpets ſounding, &amp;c. every one having a ſmall green Bough for a Sign.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>NOW Brother Souldiers, let us rather dye</l>
                     <l>Upon the ſpot, than from our Standard fly.</l>
                     <l>I fight my Head againſt a Royal Crown;</l>
                     <l>You fight for Greatneſs, Honour and Renown.</l>
                     <l>Since time began, ne're was a juſter cauſe;</l>
                     <l>Than Lives, Religion, Liberty and Laws;</l>
                     <l>We fight for Heaven, our Kingdom, Church and State,</l>
                     <l>Submitting all we have to Divine Fate.</l>
                     <l>Better we ſtand, and gain the Victory,</l>
                     <l>Than run, and by the Hands of Papiſts dye,</l>
                     <l>Even thoſe, who to accompliſh their Deſire,</l>
                     <l>Did burn our Anceſtors in <hi>Smithfield</hi> Fire.</l>
                     <l>Then let us fight with Courage, Heart and Hand,</l>
                     <l>And none give o're whilſt he hath ſtrength to ſtand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alberlo <hi>with his Forces, and draw up againſt</hi> Infortunatus<hi>'s: every one having a white Handerchief in his Hat, for a Sign.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Gentlemen, you ſee your fatal Doom,</l>
                     <l>Either to dye, or gain the cauſe of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57501:19"/>
                     <l>The Pope, your King <hi>Romanus,</hi> and his Queen</l>
                     <l>(As good a <hi>Roman</hi> Saint as e're was ſeen)</l>
                     <l>Will loſe their Right, both to our Church and State,</l>
                     <l>And be the Object of the Nations hate.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome</hi>'s cauſe is lame (I cannot well deny)</l>
                     <l>But what it wants, in Money, we'll ſupply.</l>
                     <l>Then, with a brazen Confidence, out-do</l>
                     <l>Thoſe men, who (if not ſlain) will conquer you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Since whole Files will be troubleſom and inconvenient, and ſeveral Advancings, Firings, and Fallings back, but ſuperfluous, three in a File (the Muskets lin'd with Pikes) may be enough to ſhew an Emblem of War, and demonſtrate, to the curious Spectators, the reſult of a bloody Fight.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Infortun.</hi> and <hi>Alberlo.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Make ready.</l>
                     <stage>Both at cloſe Order.</stage>
                     <l>Kneel, ſtoop, and ſtand.</l>
                     <l>Preſent.</l>
                     <l>Give Fire.</l>
                     <stage>They on both ſides flaſh their Pans.</stage>
                     <l>Recover your Arms.</l>
                     <l>Fall on, fall on, fall on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Here the Souldiers on both ſides club their Muskets, and preſent their Pikes, and come to a cloſe Fight.</hi> Flavius <hi>and</hi> Manlius, <hi>two warlike Divines, firing the Cannon. Whilſt</hi> Infortunatus <hi>driveth all before him.</hi> Romanus<hi>'s Guards give ground, whilſt others come in to aſſiſt them. The Body of</hi> Infortunatus<hi>'s Army, after a ſharp diſpute, is broke, ſeveral being killed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Where is deceitful <hi>Ferdinando</hi> now?</l>
                     <l>A Rogue, a Coward and Perfidious too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Infortunatus <hi>with his Forces, being beat, marcheth off, making good the Rear: Whilſt</hi> Alberlo <hi>purſueth.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE <hi>Alba Aula Regalis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Romanus, Cancellarius, Calamus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I long to hear what news we've from the <hi>West,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I muſt raiſe men and ſend them there in haſte:</l>
                     <l>I hear <hi>Alberlo</hi>'s beat, and all his Force</l>
                     <l>Is put unto the rout, both Foot and Horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57501:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam,</speaker>
                     <l>If it be ſo, the News will quickly fly,</l>
                     <l>But I ſuppoſe the Rumour's but a Lye,</l>
                     <l>May it prove ſo, elſe I ſhall quickly dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger in Haſte.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> the Deed is done, the worſt is paſt;</l>
                     <l>We have o'recome your Enemies at laſt.</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Myrmidonian</hi> Crew is brought to nought,</l>
                     <l>Which your Undoing and Confuſion ſought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>And is it ſo indeed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes truly ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>And what's become of my late Mortal Foe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>He's fled, but where he is, there's none doth know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Tho he be fled, he ſhall be quickly found,</l>
                     <l>Dead or alive, if he be on the ground;</l>
                     <l>And he that finds him have five thouſand pound.</l>
                     <l>But for your News, which you have brought me now,</l>
                     <l>I will requite, and likewiſe Knight you too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Both rewardeth and Knighteth him.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Manlius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> I'm come in haſte, the News to bring,</l>
                     <l>That we have beat, and took the <hi>Weſtern</hi> King,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> he in haſte did fly</l>
                     <l>Into a Field, where both aſleep did lye,</l>
                     <l>Where they were found, ſecur'd and will be here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Your News was always welcome to mine ear.</l>
                     <l>Their Lives are forfeit, they're already Dead;</l>
                     <l>And King <hi>Infortunate,</hi> ſhall loſe his Head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Don Ferdinando</hi> did your Foes betray,</l>
                     <l>Through his Deceit <hi>Alberlo</hi> gain'd the day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let the Guard that brings the Traytors in,</l>
                     <l>Let him eſcape, a Monument of Sin.</l>
                     <l>But how behav'd my Souldiers?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>Such Men as they no Age could parallel;</l>
                     <l>How can thoſe equall'd be who all excel?</l>
                     <l>Yet not the Red alone Exploits can do,</l>
                     <l>This long Black Gown hath done good ſervice too.</l>
                     <l>I fir'd the Ordinance, ſo that downright,</l>
                     <l>Some were cut off, the reſt ſoon put to flight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſhall not be forgetful to requite,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Loyaliſts that ſerv'd me in the fight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57501:20"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus <hi>Guarded, his hands bound.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>Was't you who lately made the World admire</l>
                     <l>All your Atchievements? then, huff'd with deſire</l>
                     <l>Of Greatneſs, 'gainſt my Perſon did conſpire?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Infortunatus.</stage>
                     <l>Was't you who from Mankind ſuch Friendſhip got?</l>
                     <l>Great Credit, Fame and Honour, and what not?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Invincible!</hi> (for you was termed ſo)</l>
                     <l>Tho' now like ſome mean Beaſt to th' Ax you go;</l>
                     <l>Juſt as the Lark, that flew ſo high before,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe fell down, and never roſe up more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I am the Man that lately was admir'd,</l>
                     <l>And 'againſt your Popiſh Perſon have conſpir'd;</l>
                     <l>Looſe but my hands, and you ſhall quickly ſee</l>
                     <l>The laſt Exploit of Magnanimity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll ſee your laſt breath firſt, your Perſon dead,</l>
                     <l>I'll deal with you when ſhorter by the head;</l>
                     <l>Take him away, let him in Priſon lye,</l>
                     <l>Till I appoint the day when he ſhall dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou Popiſh Prince, think'ſt thou that ever I</l>
                     <l>Was daunted? Or that I'm affraid to dye?</l>
                     <l>I'd rather fall by any Hangmans hand,</l>
                     <l>Than live a Subject under thy command.</l>
                     <l>I'll dye with courage, tho' my Death's unjuſt;</l>
                     <l>Thus the admired <hi>Phoenix</hi> one day muſt,</l>
                     <l>Drop to her Neſt, and there turn into Duſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Guards carry him to Priſon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm griev'd to ſee ſuch Spirits, in their prime,</l>
                     <l>Cut down and drop, before the Harveſt time.</l>
                     <l>I rather he in Battel had been ſlain,</l>
                     <l>Than be expoſed now to ſuch diſdain:</l>
                     <l>I gladly could prolong his wretched Life,</l>
                     <l>Were it not for my importuning Wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>Keep him in Priſon, and ſome pity take</l>
                     <l>Upon his perſon, for great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ſake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cancell.</speaker>
                     <l>A King that pardons ſuch a one as he,</l>
                     <l>Opens the door to all Conſpiracy.</l>
                     <l>Your Sacred perſon never will be ſafe,</l>
                     <l>If you to him a Pardon do vouchſafe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>With expedition, order off his Head;</l>
                     <l>Grant him a Pardon after he is dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57501:21"/>
                  <stage>Enter two Ladies, who fall on their knees.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Sir, we're come, laden with grief and tears,</l>
                     <l>To beg admittance to your ſacred ears;</l>
                     <l>And ſupplicate your Goodneſs, that you will</l>
                     <l>Forbear <hi>Infortunatus</hi> Blood to ſpill.</l>
                     <l>The pearl of Mercy is a precious thing,</l>
                     <l>And much to be deſired in a King.</l>
                     <l>If you grant this, it will renown you more</l>
                     <l>Than all the Acts of Grace e're done before.</l>
                     <l>Of all your Subjects you will gain ſuch love,</l>
                     <l>That never one will hence a Traytor prove.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <p>What can be done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Papiſſa <hi>in paſſion, with a ſtern countenance.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What beg theſe whining Whores?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Manl.</hi> They beg the King</stage>
                     <l>A ſuit of wonders, and a monſtrous thing:</l>
                     <l>To ſpare the Traytor, but himſelf is dead,</l>
                     <l>If he forgive him, till he loſe his Head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Be gone you Whores: You both deſerve to be</l>
                     <l>Laſh'd at the Cart, and pay a <hi>Bridewell</hi>-fee.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt Ladies.</stage>
                     <l>To morrow, e're it be quite Twelve a Clock,</l>
                     <l>The Traytor's Head ſhall be laid on the Block,</l>
                     <l>Where he ſhall pay for all his former guilt;</l>
                     <l>A Rebels blood is never too ſoon ſpilt.</l>
                     <l>He ſhall not have a day more to repent,</l>
                     <l>And that's the way his pardon to prevent;</l>
                     <l>I'll neither eat, nor drink, nor ſleep, nor lye,</l>
                     <l>Until the Traytor for his Treaſon dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>The SCENE a Place of Execution.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Infortunatus <hi>Guarded, the Executioner following with the Axe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this my Funeral Day, wherein I muſt</l>
                     <l>Submit to crawling Worms, and turn to Duſt?</l>
                     <l>I am more happy in my fatal Doom,</l>
                     <l>Than thoſe who live in ſlavery unto <hi>Rome;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57501:21"/>
                     <l>King <hi>Romanus</hi> cannot ſhun a fall,</l>
                     <l>When God writes <hi>MENE TEKEL</hi> on the Wall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Manlius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>Talk no more Treaſon, but Iay by your hate;</l>
                     <l>Confeſs your Crimes, and then ſubmit to Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>What Crimes? Vain-glorious Man, doſt thou</l>
                     <l>With vain pretences, come to plague me now?</l>
                     <l>Be gone baſe Slave, and from my Scaffold fly,</l>
                     <l>I'll not be taught by you the way to die;</l>
                     <l>If you prate more, I by my <hi>Axe</hi> of Steel,</l>
                     <l>Will make your Face my dying Paſſion feel.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>I do perſwade you only, if I can,</l>
                     <l>To die a Penitent good Chriſtian.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>He that doth Preach Death from a Cannons mouth,</l>
                     <l>Doth never cure, and ſeldom ſpeaks the Truth.</l>
                     <l>He that deſign'd to kill me with a Ball,</l>
                     <l>Will never raiſe me up, but make me fall.</l>
                     <l>If I have left my Peace to make till now,</l>
                     <l>It were a work too hard for me to do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Scene openeth, and all the Inſtruments of Death, with a black Coffin appear.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>By King <hi>Romanus</hi> I was hither ſent</l>
                     <l>Your long delays, and uproars to prevent;</l>
                     <l>And ſee that long'd-for Blow, that will divide</l>
                     <l>Your Head and Body, and all feuds decide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you to ſuck my Blood have ſuch deſire,</l>
                     <l>I'll quickly grant you what you do require.</l>
                     <l>Make ready Executioner, for I</l>
                     <l>Shall ſoon be in a readineſs to dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                     <l>Forgive me that which I muſt undertake,</l>
                     <l>Your Death doth make my panting heart to quake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <p>And why ſo much a Coward? 'Tis your place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                     <p>I'd rather dye than butcher up your Grace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Infort.</speaker>
                     <l>I do forgive you freely, therefore do</l>
                     <l>That which the Laws of Catholicks allow.</l>
                     <l>Come ſhed my Blood, and take this for your trouble:</l>
                     <l>All Men are Duſt, their Life's but a Bubble.</l>
                     <stage>giveth him ſome reward.</stage>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57501:22"/>
                     <stage>Here he ſtoppeth a little.</stage>
                     <l>I had the Love of all, of none the Hate,</l>
                     <l>Dandled upon the knees of Church and State,</l>
                     <l>Now muſt ſubmit my ſelf to Divine Fate.</l>
                     <stage>Layeth down his Head to the Block.</stage>
                     <stage>Stoppeth again.</stage>
                     <l>Forbear your Blow, till my mind fixed be</l>
                     <stage>To the Executioner.</stage>
                     <l>On Heaven above, and long Eternity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>After a ſhort meditation, he giveth the Executioner a ſign, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, inſtead of his Neck, ſtriketh him in the Shoulder.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Execut.</speaker>
                     <l>O cruel ſtroke! O thrice unhappy Day!</l>
                     <l>My trembling hand miſtakes the bloody way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>At the next blow the Executioner divideth his Head from his Body, and the Corps being put in a Coffin are carried away; all preſent mourning and bewailing his Fate and Tragick end.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT. IV.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The SCENE</hi> Alba Aula Regalis.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter King</hi> Romanus, Papiſſa, Cancellarius, <hi>and</hi> Calamus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Roman.</speaker>
                     <l>THis blow has ſtruck Rebellion dead, and I</l>
                     <l>Shall Reign <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Monarch till I dye.</l>
                     <l>My Foes are all evaniſh'd like a Cloud,</l>
                     <l>Diſſolv'd in Air, and periſh'd in their Blood.</l>
                     <l>Now, leſt my Kingdoms kick, and grudge to be,</l>
                     <l>Subjected to my Yoke of Popery,</l>
                     <l>I'll keep a ſtanding Army that will bring</l>
                     <l>Them to obey me, tho' a Popiſh King.</l>
                     <l>Yet here I'll ſtop the Current of my rage,</l>
                     <l>And bring no Rebels more, upon the Stage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>By force of Arms a King may ſoon ſubdue</l>
                     <l>A weak, unarm'd, untrain'd, rebellious Crew;</l>
                     <l>And afterwards compel them to inherit</l>
                     <l>The juſt reward of their Deſerts and Merit.</l>
                     <l>Yet tho' the Sword of Juſtice be a thing,</l>
                     <l>That's much to be deſired in a King:</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57501:22"/>
                     <l>Better his Subjects love him for his Good,</l>
                     <l>Than tremble at his ſhedding Seas of Blood.</l>
                     <l>Then pardon thoſe deluded Men that roſe</l>
                     <l>Againſt their King, and ſided with his Foes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll take your Counſel, for 'tis wiſe and good,</l>
                     <l>I'll live in Peace, and ſhed no Subjects Blood.</l>
                     <l>Yet will in Spite of all my Subjects Noſes,</l>
                     <l>Promote the <hi>Pope,</hi> whoever it oppoſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Think you, a drop of baſe rebellious Blood,</l>
                     <l>Can quench my Rage, that doth require a Flood?</l>
                     <l>And will incenſe the Univerſe, and Sky,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Country Rebels dye.</l>
                     <l>No, no, Revenge my Paſſion doth recruit,</l>
                     <l>And every Tree ſhall hang with human Fruit.</l>
                     <l>Go <hi>Cancellarius,</hi> ſoon, and imp your Rage</l>
                     <l>With all the <hi>Furies</hi> of this ſtubborn Age,</l>
                     <l>Fly to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> let your Revenge be hot,</l>
                     <l>Diſgorge out Halters from your fiery Throat;</l>
                     <l>Hang up thoſe Traytors of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> King,</l>
                     <l>And every Rebel to Subjection bring:</l>
                     <l>No pity take, but paſs a lawleſs Doom</l>
                     <l>On all who did not own the cauſe of <hi>Rome;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let Widows tears, and Orphans crys prevail</l>
                     <l>No more with you, than <hi>Toueſer</hi> with his Tail;</l>
                     <l>Of Human Bodies, Sinews, Blood, and Bone,</l>
                     <l>I'll Beacons build as high as <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll ſmoak in Fury, and perform your Will,</l>
                     <l>Whatever you command, be't good or ill:</l>
                     <l>I'll take no pity, but poſſeſs their Wealth,</l>
                     <l>And hang themſelves up to the Kings Good Health.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Since ſhe muſt have it ſo, pray get you gone:</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure e're long, ſhe'll pull me from my Throne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Queen, 'tis neither neceſſar, nor wiſe,</l>
                     <l>To proſecute ſo bad an Enterprize.</l>
                     <l>'Tis ſtrange, to ſee you in your Fury ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>To make your Foes your Greatneſs to ſurvive.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll have my Will, and make the Traytors fall,</l>
                     <l>I'll reign and rule, I'm one againſt them all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Canc.</stage>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57501:23"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Don Ferdinando, <hi>and falleth on his Knees.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm come to beg Forgiveneſs of my Crimes,</l>
                     <l>That's lately done, and that of older Times,</l>
                     <l>If that your Majeſty, will pardon me,</l>
                     <l>I'll henceforth ſtill a Loyal Subject be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Hence get thee gone, Thou author of Miſchief,</l>
                     <l>Thou mad'ſt the Breach, and cur'd it to my Grief.</l>
                     <l>Go live in ſhame, no puniſhment of Time,</l>
                     <l>Can equalize a Turn-Coat Traytors Crime:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                     <l>I am the Man that kept you on your Throne,</l>
                     <l>And now you ſlight, and bid get me gone,</l>
                     <l>Your foes I did out-wit on your account,</l>
                     <l>And this is all to which it doth amount:</l>
                     <l>I do deſerve to be promoted high,</l>
                     <l>And be your greateſt Subject till I dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>A Traytor once, will be a Traytor ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Turns with the Times, t' accompliſh all his Will.</l>
                     <l>Hence then thou Villain, Bane of Church and State;</l>
                     <l>I love the Treaſon, but the Traytor hate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The SCENE</hi> Villa Raſa Occidentalis.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cancellarius, <hi>with Four Conſtables.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>By King <hi>Romanus,</hi> I was hither ſent,</l>
                     <l>Treaſons and Inſurrections to prevent,</l>
                     <l>And to reward thoſe Rebels, who of late,</l>
                     <l>Strove to ſubvert both Kingdom, Church, and State.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <l>We in Obedience to our King did ſeize</l>
                     <l>Such Rebels as (their Fancy fond to pleaſe)</l>
                     <l>Did in Rebellion, riſe to overthrow,</l>
                     <l>The Government, with King <hi>Romanus</hi> Foe.</l>
                     <l>Speak but the word, we'll bring them here to you,</l>
                     <l>That you may judge them, and condemn them too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll hang them firſt, and then to Tryal bring</l>
                     <l>Such Traytors as roſe up againſt their King;</l>
                     <l>They ſhall be hurry'd hence, that others may</l>
                     <l>Be made more wary, what to do or ſay:</l>
                     <l>I'll take no pity, nor prolong the time,</l>
                     <l>But every one ſhall ſuffer for his crime.</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57501:23"/>
                     <l>Then bring them here that I may quickly eaſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Papiſſa</hi>'s Fury, and <hi>Romanus</hi> pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Three Conſtables.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Country-maid, in a ſtraw Hat, and falleth upon her knees before</hi> Cancellarius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <l>Thrice noble <hi>Sir,</hi> grave Judge, that's juſt and true,</l>
                     <l>With mournful Tears, I do petition you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Speak on fair Maid, for certainly I will</l>
                     <l>Grant your Requeſt, and your Deſire fulfil.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <l>My Sweet-Heart went to ſee the Rebels Hoſt,</l>
                     <l>And was impriſon'd there till all was loſt.</l>
                     <l>Now ſince he was detain'd by warlike Force,</l>
                     <l>And neither ſerv'd as Souldier, Foot nor Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Forgive his crime, preſerve him ſafe and ſound,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall have in Gold, Three Hundred pound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me your Gold, and I ſhall ſave his Life,</l>
                     <l>I hope you'll prove to him a loving Wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <l>Here is the Gold, I freely give it you,</l>
                     <stage>Giveth him a Bag of Guineas.</stage>
                     <l>As you have ſpoke, I hope you'll likewiſe do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me be hang'd, or elſe in Priſon lye,</l>
                     <l>To my laſt Breath, if your Sweet-Heart ſhall dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Lady</hi> Penelope, <hi>in an old torn Gown, a Page holding up her Train, in a ſorrowful manner, and preſenteth a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to</hi> Cancellarius, <hi>which he readeth thus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of Sir <hi>Roger Ringwode,</hi> Knight. Sheweth,</head>
                        <p>THat at the earneſt requeſt of my Sweet-heart, who is now my Wife, and the Bearer hereof, I was made a Knight of Honour, by King <hi>Infortunatus</hi> (of Bleſſed Memory) whom I faithfully ſerved all the time he was in the Weſt, and therefore think it contrary to the nature of Law and Chivalry, to try a Perſon of Quality with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Rabble, or hang an honeſt man with the common crew: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thought it convenient to adviſe you to let me have the judgment and ſentence of a free Parliament. But if, without any delay, you will be pleaſed to ſet me at Liberty, my Lady will give you five
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57501:24"/>pound which is more than what we are worth in the world.</p>
                        <p>Which of you do, your Petitioner will be always willing to ſerve you.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Sir</hi> R. R. <hi>Knight.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Where are thoſe pounds that are in number five?</l>
                     <l>For which I muſt preſerve a Knight alive.</l>
                     <stage>She giveth him a Bag with Five Pound.</stage>
                     <l>I'll take the mony, for 'tis none of yours,</l>
                     <l>And make you an Example to all Whores.</l>
                     <l>Your Life is forfeit, and your Husbands too,</l>
                     <l>With all the Necks of the Rebellious Crew;</l>
                     <l>Which, with <hi>Infortunatus</hi> did combine,</l>
                     <l>To proſecute his deſperate deſign.</l>
                     <l>Your name's <hi>Penelope,</hi> I heard of you,</l>
                     <l>And all your pranks of Treaſon you did do:</l>
                     <l>You gave your King a Petticoat of Scarlet,</l>
                     <l>To be a Standard, like a bold-fac'd Harlot.</l>
                     <l>Take her away, in Priſon let her lye,</l>
                     <stage>The Conſtable lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hold on her.</stage>
                     <l>For Treaſon ſhe ſhall with <hi>Sir Roger</hi> dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
                     <l>What aid could I to any Hoſt afford,</l>
                     <l>Who never could endure to touch a Sword?</l>
                     <l>'Tis true I to <hi>Infortunatus</hi> ſold</l>
                     <l>A Petticoat, which he repay'd in Gold:</l>
                     <l>But how can this ſo great a crime ſet forth,</l>
                     <l>To ſell a thing for more than thrice the worth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray ſpare the womans Life, and let her be</l>
                     <l>From her Confinement ſet at Liberty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>If I her life preſerve, I'll make her dance,</l>
                     <l>Another Jigg than ſhe can learn in <hi>France.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Constable leadeth</hi> Penelope <hi>to the Door, where he leaveth her, and returneth.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter three Conſtables, with ſeveral Priſoners chain'd; Sir</hi> Roger, <hi>in a torn Red Coat, walking foremoſt: with two women, and the Hang-man following after, with his Ropes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Rebels advance, receive your final doom,</l>
                     <l>For kicking at the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Church of Rome:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſtriving to depoſe your lawful King,</l>
                     <l>And theſe three Nations to confuſion bring.</l>
                     <l>Come hang them up, we have no need to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>To waſte our time in judging ſuch as they.</l>
                     <l>Unto the Kings good Health hang up a ſcore;</l>
                     <l>And to the Queens promote a hundred more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57501:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <l>Did you not take three hundred pounds to ſave</l>
                     <l>My Sweet-hearts life, and keep him from his Grave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caneell.</speaker>
                     <l>I mind no promiſes; come, hang them all:</l>
                     <l>We'll ſave Expence, make but one Funeral.</l>
                     <l>But ſince, ſair Maid. you would preſerve his life,</l>
                     <l>In hopes to be the young mans wedded Wife;</l>
                     <l>When dead, you ſhall receive, at my command,</l>
                     <l>Of his that which you love beſt, in your hand.</l>
                     <l>You Executioner, be ſure ſo do,</l>
                     <l>Since I have laid my ſtrict commands on you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this the Judge, by King <hi>Romanus</hi> ſent,</l>
                     <l>To do the Nation juſtice; and prevent</l>
                     <l>All Inſurrections, and again reſtore,</l>
                     <l>And mend the breach, as it hath been before?</l>
                     <l>May Juſtice ſeize ſuch Judges; for he lyes,</l>
                     <l>That calls him juſt, or good, or grave, or wiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Kiſſeth her Sweet-heart in Chains, and Exit weeping.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cancell.</speaker>
                     <l>Talk what you will, till you your ſelf confound,</l>
                     <l>I'll bear a little for three hundred pound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Roger.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a Knight of Honour, and deny</l>
                     <l>With this mad Rabble in a Rope to dye.</l>
                     <l>Come try me firſt, and after paſs my doom;</l>
                     <l>And do not hang me for the Cauſe of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could I come at him, I th' old Rogue would kill;</l>
                     <l>And, ſhould I longer live, oppoſe him ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cancell.</speaker>
                     <l>You are a ragged Knight, of Rogues the worſt,</l>
                     <l>We'll honour you, by hanging you up firſt:</l>
                     <l>You're obſtinate, miſchievous in your mind,</l>
                     <l>And have ſome wicked enterprize deſign'd.</l>
                     <l>We muſt diſpatch you ſoon with all the Crew,</l>
                     <l>Who ſuddenly ſhall bid the World adieu.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rog.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall we not have ſome time before we dye,</l>
                     <l>To fit our ſelves for long Eternity?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>No not one Minute more, for dye you ſhall,</l>
                     <l>Now inſtantly, and none prevent your fall.</l>
                     <l>Come hang them up.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhall be done, to theſe two Women here?</l>
                     <l>They ſay they're guiltleſs, and from Treaſon clear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſay they're guilty whores, already dead:</l>
                     <l>This ſhall be burnt, and that ſhall loſe her Head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57501:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                     <l>I gave a Man, whom I took for a Saint,</l>
                     <l>Money to buy thoſe things which he did want;</l>
                     <l>Who prov'd on Tryal, to be one of thoſe</l>
                     <l>Whom you repute to be your Mortal Foes:</l>
                     <l>And this is all my Crime, for which I muſt</l>
                     <l>Be burnt to aſhes, and diſſolv'd in duſt.</l>
                     <l>Yet rather ſuffer Death for Charity,</l>
                     <l>Than to a Saint a Widows mite deny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Wom.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>I lodg'd two Strangers in my Houſe all night,</l>
                     <l>And am convinc'd that it was juſt and right.</l>
                     <l>You term them Rogues, and Rebels of the Weſt,</l>
                     <l>Who did the Kingdom, Church and State moleſt.</l>
                     <l>What's that to me? I queſtion'd not at all,</l>
                     <l>Their Buſineſs, my Kindneſs was ſo ſmall.</l>
                     <l>Now innocent, to pleaſe you I muſt dye,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt all my crime is Hoſpitality.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>I have no patience, nor can I delay</l>
                     <l>Juſtice, to hear what tattling Traytors ſay.</l>
                     <l>Hang up Sir <hi>Roger</hi> firſt, that I may ſee</l>
                     <l>Three Kingdoms from his Treachery ſet free:</l>
                     <l>And after him the common crew ſhall dye,</l>
                     <l>Within the twinkling of the Hangmans eye.</l>
                     <l>As for theſe women, after all the Males,</l>
                     <l>Are put to Death, then they muſt low their Sails.</l>
                     <l>Make haſte, I'll to <hi>Romanus</hi> drink a Cup,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt theſe baſe Rebels are a hanging up.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Conſtables carry the Priſoners, under the Hangings, whence a Gibbet turneth out, like a crane, or yards Arm, with a great many men Hanging on't.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Widows mourning, and Orphans crying.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>This proſpect doth rejoyce my Soul, and I</l>
                     <l>Am overjoy'd to ſee thoſe Rebels dye,</l>
                     <l>I hope that henceforth we ſhall live at eaſe;</l>
                     <l>Only our Luſts and Appetites to pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Widows.</speaker>
                     <l>Sad ſight to ſee our Husbands and our Sons</l>
                     <l>Hang'd up, to pleaſe a crew of Friers and of Nuns:</l>
                     <l>Hell take them all, and you among the reſt,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Pointeth at</hi> Canc.</stage>
                     <l>You're all ſo bad that none can know the beſt.</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57501:25"/>
                     <l>May King <hi>Romanus</hi> from his Kingdom fly,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Gibbet turneth in again, and</hi> Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     <l>And end his Life within a Monaſtry.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The SCENE</hi> Alba Aula Regalis.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Papiſſa, <hi>big Belly'd, convey'd by</hi> Povicena, <hi>and</hi> Petrus Impoſtor.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſſa.</speaker>
                     <l>THE Tempeſt of my Fury is o'repaſt,</l>
                     <l>And now my Rage is quenched by this laſt</l>
                     <l>Blaſt of Revenge, which hath diſpers'd the Cloud</l>
                     <l>Of my Confuſion, which fell out in Blood;</l>
                     <l>Wherein I ſwim, yet do not fear to ſink;</l>
                     <l>More pleas'd with ſuch a Sea than Meat and Drink.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Povi.</speaker>
                     <l>Came think no more of Rebels, but of things</l>
                     <l>Concerning Princes, Emperours, and Kings,</l>
                     <l>The time draws nigh, wherein you muſt prepare,</l>
                     <l>To furniſh <hi>Albion</hi> with a Lawful Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>I've bore this Pillow, ſix months on my Womb,</l>
                     <l>And muſt do ſo, for three Months yet to come:</l>
                     <l>And ſince my Time of Labour doth draw nigh,</l>
                     <l>I muſt augment, and ſet the Pillow high;</l>
                     <l>Rip up the Prince, and put ſome Cotton in,</l>
                     <l>He will not cry altho you prick his Skin.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Pulleth the Pillow, from her Womb, and giveth it to the Lady, who stuffeth it with a pound of Cotton. Pointing at</hi> Petrus.</stage>
                     <l>Call in the <hi>Midwife,</hi> and <hi>Petrona</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>I'll take advice of them how I ſhall do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
                     <l>This greaſy Pillow is a naſty thing,</l>
                     <l>It ne're will be a good Prince nor a King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave off to jeſt, 'tis not a fitting time</l>
                     <l>Of that which known, would prove a deadly crime.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57501:26"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Midwife, Petrona <hi>big with Child, and</hi> Petrus Impoſtor.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>You know <hi>Petrona</hi> that I do deſign,</l>
                     <l>To add an Heir unto the Royal line;</l>
                     <l>Which muſt be done by <hi>Hocus</hi> means, when I</l>
                     <l>Shall counterfeit a Labour, and Out-cry,</l>
                     <l>You muſt be there, and privately convey</l>
                     <l>Your child to me if that it be a Boy,</l>
                     <l>When you are brought to Bed; and till you be,</l>
                     <l>I'll grunt and groan, that none may queſtion me.</l>
                     <l>You are of my Religion you know how,</l>
                     <l>That this will all the Hereticks o'rethrow;</l>
                     <l>That live in <hi>Albun,</hi> For their Prince ſhall be,</l>
                     <l>Prought up at <hi>Rome,</hi> and train'd in Popery.</l>
                     <l>Now what ſhall I give for your Child, if it</l>
                     <l>Should prove a Boy, and all my projects hit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>Five thouſand pound the matter will decide,</l>
                     <l>My Child's a Boy, it lyes in the right ſide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Five thouſand pound to make your Son a King!</l>
                     <l>This is a more than ordinary thing;</l>
                     <l>But will not ſtand what you have ſaid to do,</l>
                     <l>If to a conſtant ſecrecy you'll vow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petron.</speaker>
                     <l>I, by our Lady's Girdle and her Garter,</l>
                     <l>Rather than ſpeak one word will dye a Martyr.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petrus.</speaker>
                     <l>That will not do; but whiſpering to prevent,</l>
                     <l>On what you ſay, you's take the Sacrament.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſſa.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it be ſo; for then we'll have ſome ground,</l>
                     <l>Without delay, to pay five thouſand Pound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>But what if it ſhould prove a Girl, when ſhe</l>
                     <l>Hath got the Sum of Money? where are we?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Tho it prove ſo, I ſhall have others there,</l>
                     <l>And ſurely one will ſerve me for an Heir.</l>
                     <l>There is no need the Money to reſtore;</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Albion</hi> ſhall ſupply me ſtill with more,</l>
                     <l>'Tis for the uſe of it, I lay it out,</l>
                     <l>And it ſhall buy me too a Baby-clout,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Povi.</speaker>
                     <l>Here is your Prince, whom you ſo much adore,</l>
                     <l>'Tis weightier by a pound, than 'twas before,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Povioena <hi>giveth back the Pillow to the Queen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57501:26"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Queen</hi> Papiſſa <hi>taketh the pillow, and layeth it on her Belly, from whence ſhe had taken it.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <p>It is too low,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                     <p>Make it like mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petrus.</speaker>
                     <p>Set it higher, thus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <p>Now it is too high.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pov.</speaker>
                     <p>Pull it a little to the right ſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petrus.</speaker>
                     <p>Let it be ſo,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Now it is right.</l>
                     <l>I hope in time, to bring forth this my Son,</l>
                     <l>And end my Labour, e're it be begun.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Romanus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>What Intrigues here of ſelf-confounding Wit,</l>
                     <l>That's good for all, and yet for nothing fit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Rouſe up old Boy, altho thy vigour fails,</l>
                     <l>I will preſent thee with a —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Clappeth her hand on her Belly.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>That Prince will be my more than mor tal Foe,</l>
                     <l>And prove e're many years my overthrow.</l>
                     <l>For when the project is found out I ſhall,</l>
                     <l>With Shame, receive a ſad and diſmal Fall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſhall be your adopted Son, and Reign</l>
                     <l>As much as he had been by Nature mine:</l>
                     <l>He is your artificial Child, and ſhall,</l>
                     <l>In ſpite of all oppoſers, have the Wall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>I have a Son, my Husband never got,</l>
                     <l>Yet he's he the Father, for he doubts it not:</l>
                     <l>Believe he's yours, and your Son that's bought,</l>
                     <l>Will have, for whom, in Bed, you never wrought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>To give three Kingdoms, one was never known,</l>
                     <l>Unto a Beggar's Child to cheat his own.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll have it ſo, and if you dare deny;</l>
                     <l>My Will's a Law, and none ſhall ask me why.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petrus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> You promiſed once to reſtore</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Church of Rome,</hi> as ſhe hath been before.</l>
                     <l>This is the way, and only this will do,</l>
                     <l>A Popiſh Prince will make three Nations bow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57501:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Monſter of Dragons, muſt I turn, and be</l>
                     <l>An ancient Fop of Inhumanity:</l>
                     <l>Let it be ſo, you ſhall have my conſent,</l>
                     <l>But blame me not, when after you repent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>You muſt appoint a ſolemn day of thanks,</l>
                     <l>To pray to Heaven, to cover all our pranks;</l>
                     <l>And write to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſave us from the Lurch,</l>
                     <l>To ſing <hi>Te Deum,</hi> in <hi>St. Marry</hi>'s Church.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Were I with Child, I ſhould fear, that the prayer</l>
                     <l>Of Proteſtants, ſhould make me loſe mine Heir.</l>
                     <l>But now <hi>Papiſſa</hi> all their power defies,</l>
                     <l>Let them mock Heaven, to blind their own eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll call the Clergy, and appoint a Day</l>
                     <l>Of Faſt, whereon the Hereticks may pray,</l>
                     <l>That you may not miſcarry, but enjoy</l>
                     <l>A Popiſh Prince, their Pulpits to deſtroy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Roman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Now I am pleas'd, for 'tis a famous thing,</l>
                     <l>To be the mother of a potent King.</l>
                     <l>Come let us a play a Game at Cards for I,</l>
                     <l>Am not affraid that I'll in Child-birth dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll play at Beaſt, for by our wit we ſhall,</l>
                     <l>Confound our Foes, and make them all to fall:</l>
                     <l>Perſwading old <hi>Romanus</hi> to a thing,</l>
                     <l>That's far below the Candour of a King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhall we play for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Fifty pound a Game.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>My Duce againſt your Ace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Out fie ſhame,</l>
                     <l>That you, who muſt forgive me all my Sin,</l>
                     <l>Should proffer thus my Gravity to win.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He ſhuffleth and dealeth the Cards, and turneth up a Pick Trump.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petrus.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, Picks are Trumph.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is a Royal King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>She playeth the King of Hearts.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <p>Here I'm above him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Petrus <hi>playeth the Knave above him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>That's an unjuſt thing.</l>
                     <l>A royal Prince of his right to bereave,</l>
                     <stage>Papiſſa <hi>ſtoppeth him from taking the Trick.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Eclips'd by any Varlet, Clown, or Knave.</l>
                     <l>It will not do, but here am I my ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[playeth the Q. of Diamonds.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <p>And here am I above you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Petrus <hi>playeth the Knave above the Queen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57501:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>This is a thing that I will not allow,</l>
                     <l>I try'd the Trick, and know it will not do.</l>
                     <l>Here is my <hi>Ace of Clubs.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure I'll have that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray hold your hand, and tell me firſt for what.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Stoppeth him from taking the Trick.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is my Trea of Picks, and that is Trumps.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray take it then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Povioena <hi>in haſte, and whiſpereth Queen</hi> Papiſſa <hi>in the ear,</hi>
                     <l>telling her that Six of the Nine women with Child, were in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</l>
                     <l>deſiring her, in all haſte, to take her Labour too, and</l>
                     <l>make choice of a Prince, or Royal Heir. Exeunt Papiſſa <hi>&amp;</hi> Povioena.</l>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>I am the wit of <hi>Europe,</hi> and what's more,</l>
                     <stage>(aſide)</stage>
                     <l>The man that muſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> reſtore:</l>
                     <l>I can out-wit the wiſe, in every thing,</l>
                     <l>And by the Noſe I lead <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s King.</l>
                     <l>My policy the Queen with Child begot,</l>
                     <l>Now I'm a hatching of a Powder-plot,</l>
                     <l>That will deſtroy the Hereticks, and thoſe</l>
                     <l>That ſtrive the <hi>Roman</hi> Intereſt to oppoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Romanus, Alberlo, Cancellarius, <hi>and</hi> Calamus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>How now? doſt thou thus talk unto thy ſelf?</l>
                     <l>Like ſome Hob-Gobbling Ghoſt or Fairy-Elf.</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou invoke the Furies, from below,</l>
                     <l>To work thy King <hi>Romanus</hi> overthrow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>The Queen crys out; and I but pray that ſhe,</l>
                     <l>The Mother of a Royal Prince may be;</l>
                     <l>A Prince that may on Hereticks paſs Doom,</l>
                     <l>And make the Univerſe ſubmit to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Cry out! how ſo? methinks you're mad indeed,</l>
                     <l>Such fooliſh Fancies in your Brains to breed:</l>
                     <l>I am aſham'd ſuch idle talk to hear,</l>
                     <l>For 'tis too ſoon, I'm ſure by half a year.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>She is in Labour, for I heard her cry,</l>
                     <stage>Wipeth his eyes as he were crying.</stage>
                     <l>And I'm afraid that Queen <hi>Papiſſa</hi> dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57501:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>Good time, with eaſy Labour, like a Nun,</l>
                     <l>May ſhe enjoy, and for her pains a Son.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>A Son that may this ſtubborn Nation bring</l>
                     <l>In more ſubjection, to a potent King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The cry of a woman in Labour is heard without.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>I heard a cry, and judge that it may be,</l>
                     <l>The Queen in Labour—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>All hearken, but hear nothing.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Two Biſhops in Surplices.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray who comes here? Two Biſhops? get you gone,</l>
                     <l>I'm buſie now, but you may come anon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Biſh.</speaker>
                     <l>We hear the <hi>Queen</hi>'s in Labour, therefore we</l>
                     <l>Should in her privy Chamber preſent be,</l>
                     <l>That if ſhe have a Son we may declare,</l>
                     <l>Him <hi>Albion</hi>'s Royal, True and Lawful Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Seditious Apes, you Trumpeters of Treaſon,</l>
                     <l>Be gone, or elſe I'll ſend you both to Priſon.</l>
                     <l>What's your concernment? what ſhould you declare?</l>
                     <l>I'm old enough to look to my true Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Biſhops.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Midwife, bearing a Basket, with a naked Baby in it.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midwife.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> I'm come before your eyes to bring,</l>
                     <l>A Royal Prince, that may in time, be King</l>
                     <stage>[<hi>To King</hi> Romanus, <hi>whilſt</hi> Alberlo <hi>standeth at a diſtance.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Of theſe three Nations, pious, wiſe and juſt;</l>
                     <l>After you're Dead, and are diſſolv'd in duſt.</l>
                     <l>Come welcome him into the world, and ſee</l>
                     <l>If e're you knew a finer Child than he.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Preſenteth her Basket.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a pretty Child, take him away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <p>There never was a finer made of clay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a Girl, I vow, pray Midwife look.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <l>I from the number, have the wrong Child took,</l>
                     <l>But will bring in another.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray thee do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <p>I can another, and another too:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> Midwife.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe fooliſh women are for nothing fit,</l>
                     <l>They will betray the projects of our wit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>I'd rather give ten thouſand pound, in Gold,</l>
                     <l>Than it were known, the Child were bought and ſold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57501:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>Your words are dark, I know not what you mean.</l>
                     <l>Be bought and ſold, and children of the Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>He only talks of things, he knows not what,</l>
                     <l>Of Monks and Friars, and Nuns, and this and that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alberlo,</hi> prithee for an hour be gone,</l>
                     <l>We have a private project to be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                     <l>How e're ſo private, you may tell it me,</l>
                     <l>But ſcorn that I a burden now ſhould be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Alber.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Midwife bearing two Baskets.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Midw.</speaker>
                     <l>Here are two Children, take your choice and ſee,</l>
                     <l>Which Child is fit a royal Prince to be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They take the two Children out of the Basket, and hand them from one to another.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <p>This is the fatteſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <p>And the faireſt too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll ſeek no other, for the ſame will do.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Midwife.</stage>
                     <l>Let every <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick now ſing</l>
                     <l>In Expectation of a Popiſh King,</l>
                     <l>Who will the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> again renew,</l>
                     <l>And all the ſtiff-neck'd Hereticks ſubdue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>Call in the Biſhops, now, that they may ſee,</l>
                     <l>My Lawful Heir, and Royal Progeny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Calam.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> Will you admit them to behold</l>
                     <l>Young <hi>Innocent?</hi> and dare they be ſo bold,</l>
                     <l>With eyes and breath Heretick to prophane</l>
                     <l>The Prince that will reſtore our Church again:</l>
                     <l>We of their company ſtand not in need,</l>
                     <l>Much leſs to ſee, or touch the <hi>Royal Seed.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> ſhould I counſell'd be by you,</l>
                     <stage>[aſide.</stage>
                     <l>I ſhould my ſelf and all that's mine undo;</l>
                     <l>I might look great a while, but muſt confeſs,</l>
                     <l>I quickly ſhould be Crown, and Kingdomleſs.</l>
                     <l>You hatch'd the <hi>Prince,</hi> within your fiery Brain,</l>
                     <l>And I'm afraid the plot will prove in vain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>There is no danger, and you need not fear,</l>
                     <l>If you'll conceal all from the Subjects ear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>The Child is yours, tho Proteſtants ſhould prate,</l>
                     <l>From Clown to Prince, he's Tranſubſtantiate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:57501:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I wiſh it prove ſo, and that no man may,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Hocus</hi> Tricks, and juggling Acts betray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter two Biſhops,</hi> Manlius, <hi>and</hi> Oxonius, with Calamus Tremeb.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May't pleaſe your Majeſty,</hi> I hear the Queen</l>
                     <l>Hath theſe two Weeks, in cruel Labour been;</l>
                     <l>And now brought forth a Son, as we did pray,</l>
                     <l>When we, at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, kept Holy day,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I have a Son that is both plump and fair,</l>
                     <l>And hope will prove <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Lawful Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Papiſſa, Povioena, <hi>and the Midwife, bearing the young Prince.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>My wife you're welcome to the world again,</l>
                     <l>You have not ſpent your Labour now in vain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>I was ſo deadly ſick, I tell no ſtory,</l>
                     <l>That I was near the Gates of Purgatory.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The King ſaluteth his Queen</hi> Papiſſa, <hi>and every one kiſſeth her Hand round.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Here is your Royal Heir which I did bring,</l>
                     <stage>Taketh the Child from the Midwife, and giveth it to the King.</stage>
                     <l>From Death's dark door, to be Great <hi>Albion</hi>'s King.</l>
                     <l>Come hug and hand him all, from one another,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall not run the hazard of another.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>This Birth ſtrikes Rebels blind, turns to deſpair,</l>
                     <stage>Manlius <hi>taketh him in his Arms.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Their hopes of Conteſt for a Royal Heir.</l>
                     <l>Sedition ſinks down dead, and every Traytor</l>
                     <l>Metamorphos'd is to another creature.</l>
                     <l>Rebellion puts on black, and ſadly crys,</l>
                     <l>And Turn-coat Treaſon deſperately dies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oxon.</speaker>
                     <l>Then may he live, and wear his Father's Crown;</l>
                     <stage>Oxonius <hi>taketh the Prince in his Arms.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>And gain his Kingdom's Honour and Renown.</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Solomon,</hi> for wiſdom let him be,</l>
                     <l>And good <hi>Joſiah</hi> for true piety;</l>
                     <l>Not furious, fierce, but merciful and kind;</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Jonathan,</hi> in conſtancy of mind:</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57501:29"/>
                     <l>Like <hi>Moſes</hi> meek, Majeſtick in his word,</l>
                     <l>To ſway the Scepter, and unſheath the Sword;</l>
                     <l>To cheriſh Subjects, and promote the good,</l>
                     <l>To cut off Rebels, and caſt down the proud.</l>
                     <l>That all his Subjects may (like Flowers in <hi>May</hi>)</l>
                     <l>With peace and plenty, flouriſh in his day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe are two honeſt Hereticks, and I</l>
                     <l>Will ſtill be mindful of their Loyalty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger in haſte.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great Sir,</hi> I'm come in haſte, to let you know,</l>
                     <l>Of a more fierce and powerful <hi>Weſtern</hi> Foe.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Golden Prince</hi> from <hi>Belgium</hi> is come o're,</l>
                     <l>With fifty Sail of Ships, and on our ſhore</l>
                     <l>Hath landed Twenty thouſand men in Arms,</l>
                     <l>Which do ſurprize us with their freſh alarms.</l>
                     <l>Your Peers and Subjects joyn with him apace,</l>
                     <l>And every oppoſition gives him place.</l>
                     <l>He doth affirm and ſolemnly declare,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Royal Prince</hi> to be no Lawful Heir,</l>
                     <l>But a dark Pillow-Prince, hatch'd in the night</l>
                     <l>By Popiſh pranks, to cheat him of his right.</l>
                     <l>The groaning Nation, and the Subjects crys,</l>
                     <l>The Widows Tears, and Orphans weeping eyes,</l>
                     <l>Your baniſh'd Subjects, Liberties, and Laws,</l>
                     <l>And his own right make up a Lawful Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Of bloody War; Therefore he vows to fight</l>
                     <l>Againſt your Popiſh Crew, for his own right.</l>
                     <l>Your Souldiers, Subjects, Peers, and all accoſt</l>
                     <l>His coming in, and joyn unto his Hoſt,</l>
                     <l>Which call themſelves the Safe-guard of the Nation;</l>
                     <l>And to confirm all, here's his <hi>Declaration.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>He giveth</hi> Romanus <hi>a paper, which he looketh a little on.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>I will make haſte, to muſter all my Hoſt;</l>
                     <l>I'll fight in perſon, e're my Crown be loſt.</l>
                     <l>Go Meſſenger, in haſte, and view the Force</l>
                     <l>Of all the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Army, Foot and Horſe.</l>
                     <l>And, when you have done ſo, return to me,</l>
                     <l>And for your pains, you ſhall rewarded be,</l>
                     <stage>Exit Meſſ.</stage>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:57501:30"/>
                     <l>This is the Fruit of your confounded pranks,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Speaketh to Q.</hi> Pap.</stage>
                     <l>For which I owe the old Impoſtor thanks,</l>
                     <l>And muſt confeſs, not without provocation,</l>
                     <l>That now the Prince invaded hath the Nation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                     <l>I oft times told thee what would be the end</l>
                     <l>Of all the projects which thou didſt intend;</l>
                     <l>And hadſt thou taken but advice of me,</l>
                     <l>Thou of this Scene of Sorrow hadſt been free;</l>
                     <l>Which, now, is like to work thy fatal fall,</l>
                     <l>And, in a moment, to undo us all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>Promotion is the Curſe of men, and I</l>
                     <l>Am ſo aſtoniſh'd that I fear to dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm ſo caſt down and terrify'd in mind,</l>
                     <l>That I'm affraid a Remedy to find.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall I who have in ſo great ſplender been,</l>
                     <l>Preferr'd to be <hi>Great Albion</hi>'s Royal Queen,</l>
                     <l>Be forc'd to live in ſhame, and great diſdain,</l>
                     <l>And ſteer my courſe to <hi>Italy</hi> again.</l>
                     <l>I can but wring my hands, and ſtamp and ſtare,</l>
                     <l>And, half diſtracted, tear my curled hair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>And why ſo much affraid? I queſtion not</l>
                     <l>To ſerve him as I did the R—</l>
                     <l>I'll go, with ſpeed, an army to provide,</l>
                     <l>Which will all quarrels with the Sword decide:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Calam.</speaker>
                     <l>I will, in ſpite of every former Crime,</l>
                     <l>Turn to a State <hi>Hermophrodite</hi> of Time.</l>
                     <l>I'll whine and wheedle, ſide with every thing,</l>
                     <l>That will my projects to perfection bring:</l>
                     <l>Yet, come what will, I ſhall until I dye</l>
                     <l>Be ſure to ſerve your <hi>Soveraign Majeſty.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Calamus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Canc.</speaker>
                     <l>I've ſo behav'd my ſelf, that I ſhall dye,</l>
                     <l>If catch'd; and now can neither ſtay or fly;</l>
                     <l>I am ſo terrify'd and ſtung whith Guilt</l>
                     <l>Of Villanies, and Blood that I have ſpilt:</l>
                     <l>My Brains diſtracted, Fear doth me poſſeſs,</l>
                     <l>My Joynts do tremble for my Wickedneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                     <l>I will return to <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence I came,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrive to ſet all <hi>Europe</hi> in a flame,</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Albion,</hi> tho I ſhould contrive a Plot,</l>
                     <l>Will ſlight my Wits, and find an Antidote.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57501:30"/>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger in haſte.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I have ſurvey'd and view'd the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Hoſt,</l>
                     <l>And now three Kingdoms, with your Crowns, are loſt.</l>
                     <l>Your Guards, with all your Military Force,</l>
                     <l>Of Men and Arms, of Infantry and Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Have joyn'd themſelves unto your mortal Foes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe power the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> cannot oppoſe.</l>
                     <l>The War is ended, e're it be begun,</l>
                     <l>And there is now no Remedy but, Run.</l>
                     <stage>Drums beat and Trumpets ſound without.</stage>
                     <l>The Enemy's at hand, therefore be gone,</l>
                     <l>Preſerve your ſelf, if you ſhould loſe your Throne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>He'll take the projects, which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Crew</l>
                     <l>Have, by their Conjurations, forc'd me to.</l>
                     <l>Now I muſt ſteer my Courſe, I know not where,</l>
                     <l>And all is long of this your Royal Heir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                     <l>I'll ſtrait to <hi>Gallia,</hi> and uſe all my Arts,</l>
                     <l>Wherewith I uſe to conquer greateſt Hearts;</l>
                     <l>I'll try them all, and ſee what power I have,</l>
                     <l>To make that Generous Monarch's heart my Slave.</l>
                     <l>And if in this the Fates will be but kind,</l>
                     <l>As with this Prince I may ſuch favour find,</l>
                     <l>To grant but power ſufficient to ſubdue</l>
                     <l>This Fortunate, and too Victorious Foe;</l>
                     <l>They quickly then ſhall my reſentments ſee,</l>
                     <l>And find what 'tis to injure mighty me.</l>
                     <l>I'll bring ſuch Monſters, as ſhall make a Flood</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereticks, and Rebels Blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                     <l>May Heav'n be kind, and your endeavours bleſs,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt I invoke the Gods for your ſucceſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
                     <l>When your kind Fate to <hi>Gallia</hi> ſhall you bring,</l>
                     <l>My beſt Reſpects to the Moſt Chriſtian King;</l>
                     <l>Tell him he little doth deſerve that Name;</l>
                     <l>And alſo what a moſt prodigious ſhame</l>
                     <l>'Twill be, unto the Faith he doth profeſs,</l>
                     <l>If he my Grievances don't ſoon redreſs:</l>
                     <l>I, who to th' brink of wretchedneis am come,</l>
                     <l>And all for being true to th' <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:57501:31"/>
                     <l>The Enemy's at hand, <hi>Papiſſa,</hi> go,</l>
                     <l>And get but force to oppoſe this Mighty Foe,</l>
                     <l>We'll enter <hi>Albion,</hi> and ſuch ſpoil will make</l>
                     <l>Shall cauſe the proudeſt of their hearts to ake;</l>
                     <l>We then ſhall our Revenge moſt ſweetly taſte,</l>
                     <l>We'll Ravage, Plunder, Burn, Deſtroy, lay Waſte,</l>
                     <l>And not a Rebel leave alive at laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Queen tyeth the Prince on Father</hi> Petrus<hi>'s back, and all run out in great haſte.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:31"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <l>THe Banquet's o're, and we have fed your ſenſes</l>
            <l>With Blood &amp; Wounds, &amp; Catholick pretences.</l>
            <l>We ſhew you, in this more than ſumptuous Feaſt,</l>
            <l>The Riſe and Downfal of the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt.</l>
            <l>With Diſhes we your Appetite have fed,</l>
            <l>Such as <hi>Aſhuerus</hi> Table never had,</l>
            <l>When <hi>Symmachus</hi> had ſet before his eye</l>
            <l>A Fiſhes head, affrighted, he did fly</l>
            <l>From it: For he did take it for the head</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Theodorick,</hi> whom he murdered:</l>
            <l>Even ſo this Feaſt, preſented to your eye,</l>
            <l>Was Murther, Blood-ſhed and Phlebotomy;</l>
            <l>With Pride, Promotion, Madneſs, and what not,</l>
            <l>That can outdo a Super-treaſon Plot.</l>
            <l>Yet, as in Summer, every Hony-Bee</l>
            <l>Sucks ſweet from every object which they ſee,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:32"/>
            <l>The wiſe and prudent may reap what is good,</l>
            <l>From this our Feaſt, and after chew the Cud;</l>
            <l>And attribute the end of humane things</l>
            <l>To Providence, and not to Powerful Kings.</l>
            <l>But leſt your Diſhes of Revenge and Spite.</l>
            <l>Should not have reliſh'd with each appetite,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe you, we a Voider did afford,</l>
            <l>That did remove your Diſhes by the Sword;</l>
            <l>A Potent, Pious <hi>Prince,</hi> who by his Might,</l>
            <l>Reſtor'd three Kingdoms to their former Right.</l>
            <l>In fine then, Gentlemen, you're welcome all;</l>
            <l>Our will is good, although the Feaſt be ſmall:</l>
            <l>And if by chance we meet another day,</l>
            <l>We'll treat you with a more delicious Play.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:57501:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
